<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A present for such as have been sick and are recovered, or, A discourse concerning the good which comes out of the evil of affliction being several sermons preached after his being raised from a bed of languishing / by Nathanael Vincent.</title>
            <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27040</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09619254</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09619254</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43846</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64968)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43846)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1344:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A present for such as have been sick and are recovered, or, A discourse concerning the good which comes out of the evil of affliction being several sermons preached after his being raised from a bed of languishing / by Nathanael Vincent.</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. for Tho. Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Suffering --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:1"/>
            <p>A PRESENT For ſuch as have been SICK and are RECOVERED;</p>
            <p>Or a DISCOURSE concerning The GOOD which comes out OF THE EVIL of AFFLICTION.</p>
            <p>Being ſeveral Sermons, Preached after his being raiſed from a Bed of Languiſhing.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Vincent,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 75.</bibl> 
               <hi>I know</hi> O <hi>Lord that thy Judgments are right, and that thou in faithfulneſs haſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted me.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p> 
               <bibl>Metrodor.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY. To his Honoured Elder, and onely Brother, Mr.</hi> John Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>of</hi> North-hill <hi>in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of</hi> Cornwall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Brother!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough you affect to lead a retired Life<hi>—Procul negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is—Ut Priſca Gens mortalium:</hi> Yet I preſume this Dedication will not be unacceptable to you; ſince it ſignifies my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery
<pb facs="tcp:43846:3"/> from thoſe Diſtempers, which I thought would have left you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Brother in the World. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny indeed were concerned for me; Deſired and Prayed, that I might be ſpared and reſtored; I wiſh my Pains may be bleſst and benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to them; according to their Hopes and Expectations. They are thankful to God, that they ſtill enjoy my Labours; and I know the reſtoring of my Health, will be matter of your Thanksgiving, who are ſo full of Brotherly Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. 'Tis Pitty <hi>a Man</hi> of your <hi>Learning, Parts, and Prudence,</hi> has not appeared in a <hi>more Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Station.</hi> You might have been a more <hi>Common Good,</hi> more your <hi>Countreys Ornament</hi> and <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour,</hi> if your <hi>exceſs of Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43846:3"/> had not caſt a <hi>Veil</hi> over your <hi>great Abilities.</hi> I take it for granted, that as you have done, ſo you will ſtill adhere to <hi>His Opinion</hi> who ſaid<hi>—Bene qui latuit, bene vixit—</hi>And may you much enjoy your ſelf, <hi>My Dear Brother!</hi> and which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely better; may you enjoy <hi>much of God</hi> in your <hi>Beloved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude!</hi> May that ſmall Company, which have the Happineſs of your Acquaintance; be directed by your Advice, when they need it; and better'd by your Example! And may all the <hi>Gentry</hi> in my <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Countrey of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> look upon <hi>all Debauchery and Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, as Bruitiſh; and as much below them; as you do!</hi> I wiſh the <hi>Sword of Juſtice</hi> were in your
<pb facs="tcp:43846:4"/> hand; if it were; I perſwade my ſelf, that the Profane who deſerve it; woul <hi>feel the Edge of it;</hi> and <hi>your unblemiſht Life</hi> falling under <hi>greater Obſervation,</hi> would make thoſe, that are otherwiſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of the <hi>Spots</hi> wherewith their <hi>Lives are ſtained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know you are not a <hi>Stranger to Afflictions of diverſe kinds;</hi> This <hi>Book</hi> which I here Preſent you with; is not <hi>improper</hi> for your Peruſal. 'Tis my Deſire that <hi>no good thing may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held</hi> from <hi>You</hi> or <hi>Yours;</hi> and that all <hi>Evils</hi> by their <hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to you,</hi> may have their <hi>Nature quite alter'd,</hi> and <hi>work together for your good!</hi> May <hi>Divine Grace be ſufficient</hi> for you; till you are brought ſafe to the
<pb facs="tcp:43846:4"/> 
               <hi>Heavenly Glory and Kingdom!</hi> There are the <hi>beſt wiſhes</hi> for you that <hi>can be;</hi> and are the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, daily</hi> ones of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Affectionate Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant for Chriſts Sake.</hi> Nathanael Vincent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:5"/>
            <head>TO THE READERS, Eſpecially thoſe who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ffliction</hi> is an <hi>Argument</hi> much Diſcourſed of, and the thing it ſelf is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly felt, for <hi>Man is born unto trouble as the Sparks fly upward:</hi> And yet how <hi>few</hi> know how to <hi>improve</hi> Affliction ſo as to be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the better</hi> for it! <hi>Judgments,</hi> though dreadful ones, have <hi>little amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> this <hi>Preſent Age. Rods</hi> have been ſpent in vain; for men <hi>have received no Correction.</hi> Sin is an inveterate and ſtubborn malady hard to be cured; the
<pb facs="tcp:43846:5"/> League between the Heart and its beloved Luſts is not eaſily broken. Sinners are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable in not hearing when God <hi>ſpeaks</hi> to them; but when he <hi>ſmites</hi> them, and yet they are as if they were without <hi>Sence;</hi> how void do <hi>they</hi> ſhew themſelves both of <hi>Grace and Reaſon!</hi> Affliction <hi>in this World,</hi> is in Order to amendment; and ſo to prevent future Sorrows and <hi>Wrath in the next;</hi> And Happy thoſe who <hi>turn to Him that ſmites them;</hi> and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of feeling <hi>the uttermoſt</hi> of <hi>Sin's deſert</hi> and <hi>God's diſpleaſure!</hi> But they who will not be <hi>purged</hi> in the Furnace of Affliction <hi>now;</hi> but <hi>hold faſt Deceit and refuſe to return</hi> from their evil and deſtructive Ways; ſhall be thrown at laſt, into the <hi>flaming Furnace of Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire,</hi> whoſe heat will never <hi>end</hi> or <hi>abate;</hi> and unalterable Confirmation in Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will be a great part of their Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Miſery.</p>
            <p>The Word of God commands that the <hi>Rod ſhould be heard;</hi> and how <hi>feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly</hi> does it <hi>teach?</hi> and how dull and ſtupid are they who will not learn the Leſſons of it! The deſign of this Treatiſe
<pb facs="tcp:43846:6"/> is to make Affliction <hi>beneficial</hi> to them that labour under it; that they may not endure a great deal of Sickneſs, Pain, and trouble to <hi>no purpoſe.</hi> Corporal <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers</hi> are <hi>Spiritual Phyſick;</hi> and this Book ſhews what the <hi>Regimen</hi> Government is; which they ſhould be under that uſe it; that it may <hi>work well,</hi> and conduce to the <hi>ſoundneſs of the Mind,</hi> and the <hi>Souls Healthineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Proſperity and Health of the Soul</hi> is beyond all Conception <hi>valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Where this Health is;</hi> how <hi>clear</hi> is the <hi>Judgment!</hi> how <hi>Pure</hi> the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence! <hi>How</hi> Conformable the <hi>Will</hi> unto the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which is ſo <hi>Holy, Juſt and Good!</hi> How <hi>rightly</hi> are the <hi>Affections</hi> placed! Sin being moſt <hi>hated</hi> which is really moſt <hi>hateful!</hi> and the Lord being loved above <hi>all,</hi> who is moſt worthy to be loved! Such an <hi>Healthy Soul</hi> has a <hi>good Appetite</hi> unto <hi>ſpiritual Food,</hi> is ſtrong to <hi>walk</hi> with God and to <hi>work hard</hi> for God, 'tis ſtrong to reſiſt <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to Evil,</hi> and to maintain the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate with ſpiritual Enemies,</hi> and to <hi>bear Perſecution</hi> for the ſake of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.
<pb facs="tcp:43846:6"/> Finally, an Healthy Soul is ſtrong through Faith, Fear, Love, and Patience; to <hi>perſevere in well-doing</hi> till Glory, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Life, and Immortality are attained.</p>
            <p>Such Healthy Souls, I wiſh all afflicted Ones: and that the following Inſtructions, and Counſels may have a mighty Influence and Efficacy this way! <hi>I my Self</hi> of late have <hi>again and again drunk of the bitter Cup</hi> of Affliction. <hi>I</hi> deſire and hope to Experience more and more the <hi>Medicinal Vertue</hi> of it! And <hi>much good may this Cup do</hi> to all that have it put into their hands!</p>
            <p>The Text I handle was the <hi>firſt</hi> I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, after I come out of a <hi>Sick-bed</hi> into the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> My deſign in Publiſhing theſe Sermons, is that the <hi>Hearts</hi> of the Afflicted may be <hi>ſtedfaſt</hi> with God, <hi>after</hi> he has thrown the Rod <hi>out of his Hand;</hi> and that the <hi>Rod</hi> may <hi>bring forth more laſting Fruits of Righteouſneſs!</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Theſe Books written by the Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, are ſold by</hi> Tho. Parkhurſt <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hree Crowns <hi>at the lower end of</hi> Cheapſide, <hi>near</hi> Mercers-Chappel.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>VVOrthy Walking:</hi> Preſſed upon all that have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Call of the Goſpel:</hi> From <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>I therefore the Priſoner of the Lord beſeech you, that ye walk worthy of the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation wherewith ye are called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Spirit of Prayer:</hi> Or, a Diſcourſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Nature of Prayer is open'd, the Kinds of Prayer are handled, and the right manner of Praying diſcovered: Several Caſes about this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are Reſolved: From <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 18. <hi>Praying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> &amp;c. Unto which is added, a Direction for the Attaining the Gift of Prayer: That Family-Duty may not be omitted, nor Secret Duty diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged through Inability of Utterance and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Heaven or Hell upon Earth:</hi> Or, a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning Conſcience; on <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 16. <hi>Herein do I exerciſe my ſelf to have a Conſcience,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The True Touchſtone; which ſhews both <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Nature:</hi> Or, a Diſcourſe concerning
<pb facs="tcp:43846:7"/> 
               <hi>Self-Examination,</hi> by which both Saints and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners may come to know themſelves. Whereunto are added ſundry Meditations relating to the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>The more Excellent Way to Edifie the Church of Chriſt: Or, a Diſcourſe concerning Love: The Deſign of which is to Revive that Grace (now under ſuch decays) among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of ALL Perſwaſions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Converſion of the Soul:</hi> Or, a Diſcourſe Explaining the Nature of that <hi>Converſion</hi> which is ſincere; and Directing and Perſwading all to ceaſe their Loving Sin and Death, and to Turn to God and Live.</p>
            <p>A Warning given to Sinners to prepare for <hi>Judgment,</hi> to flee from <hi>Wrath to come,</hi> and turn from <hi>All Sin;</hi> but eſpecially the Sin which does <hi>moſt eaſily beſet them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Little Childs Catechiſm:</hi> In which the Principles of the Chriſtian Religion are in plain Words and ſhort Anſwers laid down, and ſuited to the Memories and Underſtandings of Little Children. Whereunto are added ſeveral ſhort Hiſtories, which may both pleaſe and profit them, as alſo Directions how to Pray.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt:</hi> Or, a Catechiſm, in which is contained the Sum of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> or what is neceſſary to be <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi> and <hi>done</hi> in order to <hi>Salvation.</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers being but <hi>Seventeen</hi> in number; and in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plain words, eaſie to be underſtood. Unto which is added, a Catechiſm for Conſcience;
<pb facs="tcp:43846:8"/> wherein the Conſciences of the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> the <hi>groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Profane,</hi> the <hi>Young,</hi> the <hi>meerly Mortal,</hi> and the <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> are examined, in order to their <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> and <hi>Awakening;</hi> and the Conſciences of the <hi>ſincere Chriſtians</hi> are tried in order to their <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Saints Triumph</hi> over the <hi>Laſt Enemy:</hi> In a Sermon Preached at the Funeral of that Zealous and Painful Miniſter of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>James Jane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Unto which is added, His Character. His ſore Conflict before he died: And afterwards, His Triumphant manner of departing from Earth, to the Heavenly Inheritance. On 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 55. O <hi>Death, where is thy ſting?—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſraels Lamentation</hi> at the <hi>Death</hi> of a <hi>Prophet.</hi> In a Sermon Preached at the Funeral of that Holy, Learned, and Painful Miniſter of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Cawton.</hi> And now publiſhed at the earneſt Deſire of the Hearers. On 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 1, <hi>And</hi> Samuel <hi>died, and all the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>were gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and lamented him.—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Funeral Sermon:</hi> Occaſioned by the Death of Mr. <hi>George Baker.</hi> Firſt Preached, and then Publiſhed, at the earneſt Deſire of his Relations. On 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 1. 17.<hi>—Paſs the Time of your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re in Fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Great Change:</hi> Diſcourſed of in a Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sermon, occaſioned by the Death of Mrs. <hi>Martha Thompſon,</hi> late Wife of Captain <hi>William Thompſon</hi> in <hi>Wapping.</hi> On <hi>Job</hi> 14. 14.<hi>—All the days of my appointed time will I wait till my change come.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43846:8"/>
            <head>The Good of Affliction.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſalm 119. 71.</bibl>
               <q>It is good for me that I have been afflicted; that I might learn thy Statutes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THough I appear not in the face of this Aſſembly as <hi>One riſen from the dead,</hi> yet as <hi>One raiſed from the very brink of the Grave,</hi> and am again ſent to Preach the Word of Life, the Goſpel of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Since I was laſt in this place, I have been brought very near to <hi>another World;</hi> and when I had <hi>a clearer view</hi> of it, I found that <hi>God was All;</hi> and that <hi>all this World was nothing, leſs than nothing and vanity.</hi> When Sickneſs lies heavy, and the <hi>laſt Enemy Death,</hi> ſeems entring in at the door; believe me, <hi>then</hi> it appears that Divine Favour is <hi>better than Life;</hi> the <hi>ſuccours</hi> of our <hi>merciful and faithful High-Prieſt</hi> the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; the <hi>ſupports</hi> of his <hi>Grace;</hi> and that <hi>Peace of God which paſſes all underſtanding;</hi> are things of real and of the higheſt value. I did not know
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43846:9"/> but that my Work and Life might be juſt ending; but that I might quickly be in that place, where I ſhould <hi>ſee Man no more;</hi> nor Preach any more the Word of Reconciliation. But behold! in Anſwer to the <hi>prayers of many,</hi> health is reſtored; and my Sickneſs will prove <hi>good</hi> both to <hi>me</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> if I am more <hi>ſincere</hi> in the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of; and you are more <hi>ſerious</hi> in your <hi>attendance</hi> upon my <hi>Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been <hi>Once</hi> and <hi>again</hi> brought back from the <hi>gates of Death;</hi> my obligation is increaſed to <hi>live more to God;</hi> and to endeavour to do <hi>more good to the Souls of men.</hi> I wiſh theſe ends of my life, towards the concluſion of it, may be attained more than ever. The dealings of God with me of late have been very remarkable; I deſire aright to <hi>regard the operation of his hands;</hi> and <hi>wiſely to conſider of his doings.</hi> He has come into my houſe with a <hi>Rod</hi> in his hand; and to <hi>one</hi> Member of my Family he gave a <hi>deadly blow;</hi> and others he has ſtruck down; though not quite; yet near to the Grave. I my ſelf have been of late <hi>twice</hi> ſeized with a <hi>Death threatning Malady;</hi> and am here before you all to <hi>accept the puniſhment of my iniquity;</hi> whereby <hi>infinitely worſe</hi> has been <hi>deſerved,</hi> than what I have undergone: I <hi>kiſs</hi> the Rod for the <hi>needful healing ſtrokes</hi> of it, which I have felt; and great reaſon I have to <hi>proclaim</hi> my <hi>Chaſtizers faithfulneſs</hi> and <hi>love;</hi> and how <hi>good 'tis for me that I have been afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43846:9"/>
            <p> In the words which I have read; theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars are obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is an Exerciſe <hi>ſharp and ſore</hi> to <hi>Nature;</hi> and which will put <hi>Grace</hi> upon the <hi>Tryal,</hi> and prove the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> of it; and this Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe is <hi>Affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Perſon</hi> thus exerciſed is the Pſalmiſt, who was both <hi>Saint</hi> and <hi>Preacher.</hi> Saints are afflicted, that they may be more throughly ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified: Preachers are afflicted, that they may Preach and labour to better purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From <hi>whom came</hi> the Pſalmiſts Affliction? the <hi>Rod</hi> which he felt was in <hi>God's hand:</hi> To <hi>Him</hi> he ſpeaks in the Text; being ſenſible he had to do with God; and God had to do with him. <hi>Rods,</hi> though of <hi>ſins meriting;</hi> are of <hi>God's making:</hi> All <hi>bitter Cups,</hi> are of <hi>God's own mingling:</hi> the <hi>kind,</hi> the <hi>meaſure,</hi> the <hi>continuance</hi> of Affliction is of the <hi>Lord's own appointment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Iſſue</hi> of Affliction follows; it iſſued <hi>well</hi> in the Pſalmiſts <hi>trueſt good;</hi> it made him really better than he was before; therefore good for him indeed: It was <hi>medicinal to his Soul;</hi> the <hi>inward man was more renewed;</hi> heart and life both very much amended.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Here is a <hi>demonſtration;</hi> that Affliction was thus beneficial to him; becauſe <hi>in the School of Affliction</hi> he learnt <hi>God's Statutes better;</hi> he learned to <hi>prize</hi> them; for in the following verſe, he preferred them <hi>before thouſands of gold and ſilver:</hi> And thus looking upon them as an <hi>invaluable</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43846:10"/> 
               <hi>Treaſure,</hi> here is an intimation that he <hi>kept</hi> them, with a conſcientious and affectionate care and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</p>
            <p>I raiſe two Doctrines from the words.</p>
            <p>The <hi>one</hi> is, <hi>That Saints are afflicted for their good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>other</hi> is, <hi>That the Rod of God is a means to make his Word to be the better learned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> I. I begin with the firſt of theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; <hi>That Saints are afflicted for their good;</hi> they are the better and happier for being chaſtened; <hi>Job</hi> 5. 17. <hi>Behold, happy is the man whom God correcteth; therefore deſpiſe not thou the chaſtening of the Almighty.</hi> Chaſtening is <hi>deſpiſed,</hi> if it be lookt upon only as a <hi>miſery;</hi> which has ſo great a tendency to <hi>promote</hi> our <hi>happineſs;</hi> Jam. 5. 11. <hi>Behold we count them happy which endure: Ye have heard of the patience of</hi> Job, <hi>and have ſeen the end of the Lord; that the Lord is very pitiful, and of tender mercy.</hi> Both theſe paſſages have <hi>Behold</hi> prefixed to them; they ſeem <hi>Paradoxes</hi> to carnal reaſon; but if the Eye of the Underſtanding be opened to look into the matter, it will be perceived that Affliction and Happineſs are not <hi>diſparata,</hi> which never meet in the ſame ſubject; the Saints are the more bleſſed the more they are corrected! That paſſage may be called a <hi>Threatning,</hi> becauſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43846:10"/> is a puniſhment of Iniquity; and alſo a Promiſe, becauſe Correction ends in Amendment; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 30, 31, 32, 33. <hi>If his Childrrn for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake my Law, and walk not in my Judgments; If they break my Statutes, and keep not my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; then will I viſit their Tranſgreſſion with a Rod, and their Iniquity with Stripes: Nevertheleſs my loving-kindneſs will I not utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take from him, nor ſuffer my faithfulneſs to fail.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this Doctrine I ſhall,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Demonſtrate the <hi>Truth</hi> of it <hi>by ſeveral Arguments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall <hi>ſpecifie what that good</hi> is which accrews to the Saints by Affliction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conclude with the <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place I am to demonſtrate that Saints are afflicted for their good.</p>
            <p>The Arguments demonſtrating this, are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Afflictions are of <hi>God's own ſending, whoſe goodneſs is manifeſted in</hi> the ſending of them. The Afflictions which the Saints feel, are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in Heaven for them. <hi>Job</hi> regards not ſo much the malice of Satan, nor the injuſtice and violence of Man, in that ſore Calamity which ſo ſuddenly fell upon him; but his Eye looks as high as God in it; <hi>Job</hi> 1. 21. <hi>The Lord has taken away; bleſſed be the Name of the Lord!</hi> Well may he be bleſſed; for the Lord <hi>ceaſes not to be good</hi> to his People when he takes a <hi>Rod into</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43846:11"/> 
               <hi>his hand to beat</hi> them. Afflictions in Scripture are compared to Waters; and theſe Waters come out of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and <hi>ſavour</hi> of it. Give me leave to <hi>ſearch the Springs</hi> of theſe Waters, and trace them to the Fountain head; and upon due ſearch it will be found that they flow from the <hi>trueſt love,</hi> the <hi>wiſeſt care,</hi> the <hi>greateſt faithfulneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Saints Afflictions flow from <hi>the trueſt love;</hi> Heb. 12. 6. <hi>Whom the Lord loves, he chaſtens; and ſcourgeth every Son whom he receives.</hi> Now To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Love, are to be reckoned among the good things, not the evil. The Lord chaſtens his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whom he delights in; that he may make them more lovely; and his delight in them may be the greater. Indeed in Nature 'tis otherwiſe; <hi>The ſame Fountain cannot at the ſame place ſend forth ſweet Water and bitter; Jam.</hi> 3. 11. Yet certain it is, that <hi>all</hi> the <hi>ſweetneſſes,</hi> and <hi>bitterneſſes</hi> of a Chriſtian, come from <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> the <hi>Everlaſting Love</hi> of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Saints Afflictions flow from the <hi>wiſeſt care.</hi> God cares for his People, and bids them caſt all their care upon him; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Caſting all your care upon him, for he careth for you.</hi> When <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s countenance was full of rage; and the three Children were threatned with a fiery Furnace ſeven times heated; they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of God's care; and had ſaid and ſtood to it; <hi>We are not careful to anſwer thee;</hi> but <hi>be it known to thee, we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Golden Image thou haſt ſet up; Dan.</hi> 3.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43846:11"/> 16, 18. God's care of them was great in this extreme peril. And he cares for all his Saints; their <hi>life,</hi> their <hi>health,</hi> their <hi>comforts</hi> are <hi>precious</hi> in his Eyes; and they ſhall not be toucht, but when neceſſity and conveniency calls for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Saints Afflictions ſlow from the <hi>greateſt faithfulneſs.</hi> The Church in the very depths of trouble cries out, <hi>Great is thy faithfulneſs!</hi> Jer. 3. 23. <hi>I know, O Lord,</hi> ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>that thy Judgments are right; and that thou in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs haſt afflicted me; Pſal.</hi> 119. 75. The Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians faithfulneſs appears in giving very bitter Potions, which are a means to ſave the Patients life. Sharp Afflictions are often neceſſary to rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the health of the Soul; divine faithfulneſs is manifeſted in this method of recovery. This faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God <hi>debates</hi> with the <hi>Rod when it ſhoots forth,</hi> leſt it ſhould be <hi>too heavy,</hi> and rather <hi>make an end</hi> of, than <hi>mend</hi> his Children; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 8. <hi>In meaſure when it ſhooteth forth thou wilt debate with it; he ſtayeth his rough Wind in the day of the Eaſt Wind:</hi> For if both theſe Winds ſhould blow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the Saints might not be able to ſtand againſt them. That is the <hi>firſt</hi> Argument to prove the goodneſs of Affliction; it is of <hi>God's ſending;</hi> and in ſending of it, his <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>care,</hi> and <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> is manifeſted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Afflictions are ſent with a <hi>deſign that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Saints may be benefited.</hi> He does not <hi>afflict willingly, nor grieve the Children of Men:</hi> The Lord ſees they have <hi>need of it,</hi> and therefore <hi>they are in heavineſs:</hi> But when Affliction is as it were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43846:12"/> 
               <hi>plowing upon the backs</hi> of the Saints; and <hi>long and deep furrows</hi> are made; the Lord at that very time is <hi>ſowing</hi> both <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>joy;</hi> and how <hi>plentiful</hi> will the <hi>Harveſt</hi> be! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97. 11. <hi>Light is ſown for the righteous, and joy for the upright in heart;</hi> Heb. 12. 11. <hi>Chaſtening does yield the peaceable fruits of righteouſneſs to them who are exerciſed thereby.</hi> Earthly Parents are oftentimes tranſported with <hi>paſſion,</hi> and act after their own humour and pleaſure in correcting of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and then their Children are rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to anger, and diſcouraged, than amended. But hereby it moſt evidently appears; 'tis good for the Saints that they are afflicted; becauſe their Father, who is the Father of Spirits, does cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtize <hi>his Children for their profit,</hi> that is, their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual profit and advantage; that they may be partakers of his holineſs; <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 10. And the truth is, we are never <hi>more profited,</hi> than when we are <hi>moſt ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Afflictions of the Saints are <hi>diſpenſed to them through Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> therefore they muſt needs be good for them; for <hi>nothing</hi> comes to them through <hi>Him,</hi> that is <hi>otherwiſe.</hi> He has <hi>born the Saints ſins,</hi> ſo that they are neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned nor commanded by them: He unſtings death, before it ſeizes upon any of his Members; ſo that the venom and poiſon of death, which is ſin, is gone; and death without a ſting is not to be dreaded. And Chriſt has alſo born the Saints <hi>Sickneſſes</hi> and <hi>Infirmities; Mat.</hi> 8. 17. and ſo the <hi>cauſe</hi> of them is removed: God does not demand
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43846:12"/> 
               <hi>ſatisfaction to his Juſtice</hi> in the Afflictions of his People; for Chriſt by his Sufferings has made full Satisfaction. He does not exact <hi>Law Payment</hi> of them, for Chriſt was made <hi>under the Law,</hi> and fulfilled it, and <hi>bare the Curſe</hi> due to Believers for tranſgreſſing of it. The Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, how does it alter Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions! it turns them into profitable and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Medicines! Oh <hi>Bleſſed Troubles,</hi> in which Chriſt himſelf <hi>Sympathizes</hi> with Souls that are troubled! <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 9. <hi>In all their Afflictions, he was afflicted, and the Angel of his Preſence ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them.</hi> 'Tis certain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y good to be in the <hi>Furnace,</hi> if the <hi>Son of God</hi> be there with us; to mitigate the heat of it, and to conſume the <hi>droſs</hi> only, while the <hi>Metal is ſecured,</hi> and <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Afflictions make the Saints <hi>Conformable to Chriſt their Head,</hi> and 'tis never better with the Members; than when there is the greateſt reſemblance in them to their Head and Lord. He was <hi>perfected</hi> as Mediatour <hi>through Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</hi> At length he ſuffer'd ſo much, that he cried out, <hi>It is finiſhed;</hi> he paid a full Price for his Churches Redemption; and made her Everlaſting Peace. His Members alſo muſt be <hi>perfected</hi> in <hi>Mortification</hi> and Holineſs by <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings</hi> alſo; theſe help to pull down Pride, and Self-confidence; to tame the Fleſh, and to check and kill the Affections and Luſts of it. Happy Afflictions! which make afflicted Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers more like to their Lord in whom they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43846:13"/> do believe! In <hi>Conformity</hi> to Chriſt lies our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and Safety. This Conformity is in a ſpecial manner deſigned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 29. <hi>For whom he did foreknow, he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the Image of his Son, that he might be the firſt born among many Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> The Image of the <hi>Earthly Adam</hi> is our <hi>Shame,</hi> the Image of the <hi>Heavenly Adam</hi> is our <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Afflictions of the Saints are <hi>under a Promiſe that they ſhall work for good.</hi> The <hi>Medicines</hi> which the great Phyſician of Souls gives to Believers do <hi>Work well,</hi> as they are very proper, ſo very Effectual, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 28. <hi>We know</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, we are <hi>aſſured</hi> of it by <hi>Faith,</hi> and we find it <hi>true</hi> by <hi>Experience;</hi> That <hi>all things Work together for good, to them that love God; who are called according to his purpoſe.</hi> God himſelf <hi>will Work</hi> along with Calamities and Troubles of <hi>all ſorts,</hi> and bring forth <hi>much good</hi> out of the <hi>very worſt</hi> of them. They work upon the <hi>Hearts</hi> of the Saints, and better the <hi>frame</hi> and <hi>temper</hi> and <hi>Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them.</hi> They work upon their <hi>Tongues,</hi> and lay a <hi>Bridle</hi> upon them; and bring them under the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Holineſs, Love and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> they work upon the Actions, making them more agreeable to that <hi>Rule,</hi> which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever walk according to, <hi>Peace and Mercy ſhall be upon them.</hi> Nay Afflictions work no leſs than <hi>Glory,</hi> and when the Apoſtle conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Weight and Eternity of that Glory,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43846:13"/> he made light of the heavieſt Afflictions; the Benefit is unconceiveably vaſt, that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is reaped from them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17. <hi>For our light Affliction which is but for a Moment, worketh for us a far more Exceeding and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal weight of Glory.</hi> Not that Affliction and Suffering though for Righteouſneſs ſake, does <hi>deſerve this Glory,</hi> but it makes it the more Minded and Deſired, and is a means to make us meet for the Enjoyment of it; and the Promiſe is ſure, that if <hi>we ſuffer</hi> according to the Will of God, we ſhall alſo <hi>Reign with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Afflictions muſt needs be granted to the Saints, <hi>for they purge out the worſt evil of all; and that is Sin.</hi> Oh! <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>out of meaſure ſinful Sin!</hi> No Name ſo bad as thy own! No Evil ſo great as thou art! Let all <hi>the Calamities of the Earth,</hi> and all the <hi>Miſcries of Hell,</hi> be put into the <hi>One Scale together;</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> into the <hi>other;</hi> as Sin is the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of them all, ſo it will <hi>outweigh</hi> them all. 'Tis the <hi>abominable thing which Gods Soul hates.</hi> 'Tis the great <hi>Evil and Enemy whereby Mans Soul is ruined.</hi> How much is Affliction good for! ſince 'tis a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign means, whereby ſuch an Evil as Sin, is purged away, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 9. <hi>By this therefore ſhall the Iniquity of</hi> Jacob <hi>be purged, and this is all the Fruit, to take away his Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The Afflictions of the Saints are means to <hi>prevent their Eternal Sufferings in the other World.</hi> The Rod is of their Fathers own Appointment,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43846:14"/> 
               <hi>to deliver his Childrens Souls from Hell.</hi> Preſent <hi>Caſtigation</hi> prevents Eternal <hi>Condemnation,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 32. <hi>But when we are judged, we are chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Lord, that we might not be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the World.</hi> Not that, Sin has not <hi>ill demerit enough</hi> to make us obnoxious to Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in <hi>both Worlds;</hi> not that <hi>Chaſtizement</hi> makes <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for Tranſgreſſion: But it makes the Saints <hi>to fly to the Lord Jeſus,</hi> for the making up of all breaches between God and them; which Sin has made; and 'tis effectual to make them truly Humble and Penitent: Now Faith and Repentance have the Promiſe of Life annexed to them. <hi>Whoſoever believes on the Son of God, ſhall not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life,</hi> Joh. 3. 16. And Repentance is ſaid to be <hi>unto Salvation</hi> and conſequently <hi>not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of,</hi> 2 Cor. 7. 10.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Afflictions bring the <hi>Saints nearer to God;</hi> and to be near to Him, how <hi>good is it for them!</hi> Pſal. 73. 28. God expects a more ſerious ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a nearer approach when he afflicts his People, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5. 15. <hi>I will go and return to my Place, till they acknowledge their Offence, and ſeek my Face; in their Affliction they will ſeek me early.</hi> And his People Anſwer his Expectation, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6. 1. They ſay, <hi>Come and let us return to the Lord, for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he has ſmitten, and he will bind us up.</hi> Afflicted Saints inquire after God, they come with their Penitential Acknowledgments; and deſire more fully to know wherefore it is that he Contends;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43846:14"/> that the ground of the Controverſie may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. <hi>It is meet</hi> that the Afflicted Saint <hi>ſhould ſay,</hi> and with <hi>his Heart he does</hi> ſay it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. <hi>I have born Chaſtiſement, I will not offend any more; that which I ſee not, teach thou me, if I have done Iniquity I will do no more,</hi> Job 34. 31, 32. All that is within him now yields unto God, and being <hi>melted</hi> in the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of Affliction, he deſires to be caſt into the <hi>mould</hi> of his Word. Happy blows! which drive the Saints to God, and ſtrengthen their Reſolutions to abide with God! Thus have I <hi>demonſtrated</hi> that <hi>Saints</hi> are afflicted <hi>for their good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Second Place, I am to <hi>ſpecifie that good which accrews to the Saints by Affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. One good conſequent of Affliction, <hi>is a greater Power of Spiritual Diſcerning.</hi> Prov. 29. 15. <hi>The Rod and Reproof give Wiſdom.</hi> If Mans Rod does ſo, then it follows, that the Rod of God does it much more. Gods <hi>Teaching</hi> accompanies his <hi>Chaſtning,</hi> and <hi>who Teaches like him?</hi> Afflictions clear the Eye of the Soul; ſo that it is more <hi>Single</hi> and <hi>Piercing.</hi> It ſees now plainly, through the deceitfulneſs of Sin. It ſees the <hi>Worlds emptineſs</hi> and Vanity, and an <hi>End</hi> of all its Perfection. It ſees the <hi>Subtilty of the old Serpent,</hi> and how much it concerns all neither to believe, nor follow him. It diſcerns the <hi>Inſufficiency, Weakneſs,</hi> and <hi>Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs</hi> of <hi>Self;</hi> and that 'tis neither to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43846:15"/> in, ſought, or pleaſed. It ſees the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of</hi> that <hi>Salvation</hi> which is in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and what an <hi>All-ſufficient and Eternal Portion</hi> the <hi>Lord Jehovah</hi> is. And the Afflicted Saints Knowledge of all this, is more than Notional. He knows by Experience as well as Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Evil of Sin; and the <hi>unſuitableneſs</hi> of the World is <hi>plain</hi> to his <hi>Spiritual Senſe,</hi> and ſo is the <hi>Power of the Grace</hi> of Chriſt. In Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the <hi>other World opens,</hi> and the Eye <hi>looks</hi> into it; and what a <hi>Cypher</hi> then is this whole Globe of Earth and Waters! The Apoſtles <hi>outward Man periſhed:</hi> He was exerciſed with Affliction; and what <hi>clear views</hi> had he then of <hi>things unſeen?</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 16, 18. <hi>For which cauſe we faint not, but though our outward man periſh; our inward man is renewed day by day. While we look not at the things that are ſeen, but at the things that are not ſeen; for the things that are ſeen are Temporal, but the things that are not ſeen are Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Another good Conſequent of Affliction, is <hi>a more Pure and tender Conſcience.</hi> How great a Miſery is it to have a ſtupid Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that is <hi>without</hi> or <hi>paſt</hi> feeling! When a man has all his <hi>own Guilt,</hi> and the <hi>Wrath of God</hi> abiding upon him; not a <hi>Promiſe in the Bible</hi> belonging to him, all the <hi>threatnings full char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> with <hi>Curſes and Woes,</hi> juſt <hi>ready to be diſcharged at him:</hi> And He himſelf is upon the very brink of Hell, juſt ready to tumble in every Moment; and yet is <hi>altogether unſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43846:15"/> of any <hi>danger!</hi> Such a ſenſeleſs Conſcience is a <hi>deadly Sign;</hi> it argues Spiritual Death to have full Power; and Eternal Death to be at the door; In the <hi>depths of Deſpair</hi> there is more <hi>Probability</hi> of Salvation; than in the <hi>heighth of Preſumption.</hi> But Affliction <hi>ſtartles the Conſcience,</hi> how quick is its <hi>Sight</hi> and <hi>Senſe then!</hi> The Saints have recourſe to the <hi>Blood of</hi> Chriſt to <hi>purge their Conſciences</hi> from all <hi>the Dead works</hi> in which they have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly employed. And that Blood is ſufficient for their <hi>Purgation and Peace,</hi> Heb. 9. 14. <hi>How much more ſhall the Blood of Chriſt, who through the Eternal Spirit offered up himſelf without Spot to God; purge your Conſciences from dead Works, to ſerve the Living God!</hi> And afflicted Saints are exceedingly <hi>afraid</hi> of making <hi>new wounds</hi> in their Conſciences, ſince the <hi>Smart</hi> of <hi>former wounds</hi> in their Spirits was ſo <hi>intolerable,</hi> Lam. 3. 19, 20. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring my Affliction and my Miſery, the Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood and the Gall; my Soul has them ſtill in remembrance and is humbled in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Another good Conſequent of Affliction, is <hi>the Mortification of the Sin of Pride.</hi> Pride is a Sin <hi>hateful to God,</hi> it <hi>ſtrikes</hi> at his <hi>Glory</hi> which <hi>God aims at</hi> in every thing he does. And Pride is very <hi>hurtful</hi> to man, 'tis the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of the Help which Divine Grace af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords; for God <hi>who gives Grace to the Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> inſtead of <hi>aſſiſting</hi> does <hi>reſiſt the Proud,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 5. And this Pride is the forerunner
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43846:16"/> of <hi>falls</hi> into <hi>Sin</hi> and Ruine, therefore ſays <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon. Pride goes before Deſtruction and an haughty Spirit before a fall</hi> The Lord can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure this Pride in his Saints, and Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is ſent to kill it: The Troubles which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> met with in the Wilderneſs, when they were encountred with <hi>Fiery Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents and Scorpions, and Drought;</hi> and many other Calamities, the end of them all was to <hi>Humble them and Prove them, and to do them good in the latter end.</hi> Deut. 8. 15, 16. A Saint who comes out of the Fire of Affliction with a Meek and humble Spirit; his high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits and Thoughts of himſelf all caſt down; ſeeing himſelf to be nothing, but what he is by the Grace of God; this man looks <hi>like Silver coming out of a Furnance of Earth puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſeven tunes,</hi> and what a ſhining <hi>bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and luſtre</hi> is upon him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Another good Conſequent of Affliction is <hi>a more perfect Subjection of the whole Man to God.</hi> There is a Submiſſion to Him, by a <hi>Penitential Acknowledgment</hi> of Offences againſt him, and <hi>juſtifying</hi> of him in his <hi>ſevereſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations,</hi> Neh. 9. 33. <hi>Howbeit thou art juſt in all that is brought upon us, for thou haſt done Right, but we have done Wickedly.</hi> There is a Submiſſion to <hi>his Righteouſneſs,</hi> a great ſenſe, that 'tis by the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>One</hi> onely the <hi>ſecond</hi> Adam; that the <hi>Free Gift comes upon all</hi> that are in him <hi>unto Juſtification of Life.</hi> Rom. 5. 18. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 4. <hi>Chriſt is the end</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43846:16"/> 
               <hi>of the Law for Righteouſneſs to every one that believeth.</hi> There is likewiſe a <hi>Subjection of Body and Soul</hi> unto the <hi>commands</hi> of God, which reach the <hi>whole man,</hi> and require ſervice from the <hi>whole.</hi> And Affliction quickens Deſires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Grace, to keep theſe Precepts better; ſo that there may not be <hi>a wandring</hi> from them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 10. <hi>With my whole Heart have I ſought thee, oh let me not wander from thy Commandments.</hi> Sin's ſervice becomes more irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, the Law of Sin more grievous; but the Lords ſervice is accounted <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> Rom. 6. 22. <hi>But now being made free from Sin, and become Servants to God, ye have your Fruit unto Holineſs, and the end Everlaſting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Another good Conſequent of Affliction is <hi>greater Exactneſs and Spirituality in Duty and Obedience.</hi> Affliction cauſes Saints to Eye <hi>their Hearts</hi> more, which <hi>God</hi> does Eye <hi>Principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Lip Labour, Bodily Exerciſe, outward Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies; are perceived to be, when <hi>alone,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together <hi>inſignificant.</hi> Afflicted Saints give God their very Hearts: The <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Vigour</hi> of their <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Affections:</hi> 'tis very evident to them, that He alone is Worthy of them. And <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not <hi>Self,</hi> has their Confidence, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>We are the Circumciſion, who Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in the Spirit; rejoice in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and have no Confidence in the Fleſh.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Saints lift up their Souls to God; in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43846:17"/> his hand they are ſafe, and this is the Way to have them ſatisfied and fill'd with Joy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. 4. <hi>Rejoice the Soul of thy Servant for unto thee O Lord do I lift up my Soul.</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to God are performed with <hi>more Grace,</hi> and Duties to Man are done with a greater <hi>regard</hi> unto <hi>God</hi> Himſelf. Gods Approbation is more minded; and the Eye being <hi>ſingle</hi> looks not ſo much at other things, but aims at this, that God <hi>in all things may have Glory;</hi> which indeed of Right appertains to Him.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Another good Conſequent of Affliction is a <hi>more full and compleat Victory over the World, and ſilencing the God of it.</hi> When Sickneſs ſeizeth upon the Saints; the <hi>Love</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> is hereby ſtruck <hi>more dead.</hi> The World is <hi>out of Countenance,</hi> and aſhamed <hi>now</hi> to appear; it's <hi>alluring Power</hi> and <hi>Charms</hi> are <hi>all gone.</hi> And Satan the God of it, does not ſo much care <hi>now to offer</hi> it. Mammon can neither cure the diſeaſed Body, nor eaſe the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Mind. Affliction takes off the <hi>fine Mask</hi> upon <hi>Mammons Face,</hi> and then 'tis plainly ſeen how <hi>ſorry a Maſter</hi> he is; and how poor all his ſtore. The World cannot yield <hi>true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment</hi> to any, for that <hi>little while</hi> they are the Inhabitants of it; and can any thing of <hi>this World</hi> be carried away into <hi>another World?</hi> Ah no! 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 7. <hi>For we brought nothing into this World, and 'tis certain we can carry nothing out.</hi> He that has moſt of the World,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43846:17"/> what is it all to him, when he is <hi>leaving</hi> the World and <hi>all behind</hi> him?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the <hi>greateſt Poſſeſſour</hi> of Earthly Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>lying</hi> upon a <hi>Death-bed;</hi> in his fainting Fits, and dying Agonies; lay ſome baggs of Gold upon his Pillows, bring in the ſweeteſt Conſort of Muſick, ſhew him the coſtlieſt Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wore; let a Table be ſpread and furniſht with the choiceſt Dainties, and let the greateſt Beauties ſtand by him, proffering themſelves and their ſervice to him. Alas! Alas! what's all this to a Man that is breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out his laſt Breath; and ready to appear and give an account of himſelf unto the Judge of all? Affliction gives a <hi>ſmart Admonition,</hi> that this World is to be contemned in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the <hi>better and enduring Subſtance.</hi> Satan, notwithſtanding his Subtlety, is eaſily baffled in Affliction; think ſeriouſly of Death and Judgment; and <hi>all</hi> that He offers is <hi>juſt nothing;</hi> though he ſhould make as large an offer, as he did to Chriſt in the hour of his Temptation, when he <hi>ſhewed him all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World and the Glory of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Another good Conſequent of Affliction, is <hi>an Increaſe of Grace, and an abundance of the Fruits of Righteouſneſs.</hi> Wicked men <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not Correction,</hi> being put into the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, they are found, and <hi>rejected</hi> as <hi>Reprobate Silver;</hi> but the Correction of the Saints, is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43846:18"/> the Probation, Augmentation, and evidencing of the Grace of God in them. <hi>Faith</hi> is tried, and by trial is ſtrengthned, <hi>Patience, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Hope</hi> augmented, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 3, 4, 5. <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation worketh Patience, Patience Experience, Experience Hope, and Hope maketh not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, becauſe the Love of God is ſhed abroad in our Hearts by the Holy Ghoſt which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to us.</hi> The Lords tender Compaſſions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his afflicted Children, exceedingly endears him their Father to them! His gracious Viſits, His ſtretching forth his own Everlaſting Arm for their Suſtentation, when ready to ſink under their Burthens; His remembring Mercy in the greateſt Severity, His being within call, and readineſs to hear and help; fills their Hearts with Love, and Reſolution to live and cleave to him. With how much Tenderneſs and Compaſſion, does the Lord expreſs himſelf towards his afflicted ones! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. 33. <hi>For the Lord heareth the Poor and deſpiſeth not his Priſoners.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 24. <hi>For he hath not deſpiſed nor abhorred the Affliction of the afflicted, neither hath he hid his Face from him; but when he cried unto him he heard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saints are great gainers by Affliction, becauſe <hi>Godlineſs</hi> which is <hi>great Gain,</hi> which is <hi>profitable for all things,</hi> is more powerful than before. The <hi>Rod</hi> of Correction by a <hi>Miracle</hi> of Grace, like that of <hi>Aarons,</hi> Buds and Bloſſoms, and brings forth the Fruits, of Righteouſneſs, which are moſt excellent. A rare ſight it is indeed to ſee a man
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43846:18"/> coming out of a bed of Languiſhing, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Furnace of Affliction; more <hi>like</hi> to <hi>Angels</hi> in <hi>Purity,</hi> more <hi>like</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> who was <hi>Holy, Harmleſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled, and ſeparate from Sinners;</hi> more <hi>like</hi> unto <hi>God himſelf,</hi> being <hi>more exactly Righteous in all his ways,</hi> and more exemplarily <hi>Holy in all manner of Converſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Another good Conſequent of Affliction, is <hi>an high eſteem of Time, and affecting Apprehenſions of Death, Judgment, and Eternity.</hi> Affliction brings Death within view. <hi>Jobs Calamity</hi> makes his <hi>Mortality</hi> much thought of; the things of the <hi>World</hi> had <hi>left him;</hi> he ſpeaks as a man juſt ready to <hi>leave</hi> the World, <hi>Job</hi> 17. 1, 13, 14. <hi>My Breath is corrupt, my Days are extinct, the Graves are ready for me. If I wait the Grave is my Houſe, I have made my Bed in the Darkneſs. I have ſaid to Corruption, thou art my Father; and to the Worm, thou art my Mother and my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> He claims kindred to the Worms and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, Death was moſt familiar to his Thoughts; and in his Imagination, the Grave was his Bed already.</p>
            <p>Now at Death the Saints conſider, that <hi>Time</hi> comes to <hi>a full ſtop;</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> will follow, and <hi>fix</hi> them in <hi>Eternity.</hi> It is of great uſe to us; when our <hi>Thoughts dwell</hi> in Eternity, before we our ſelves enter upon Eternity; this makes an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Happy Eternity infinitely deſireable</hi> in our Eyes! And how do we <hi>look unto Jeſus!</hi> through
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43846:19"/> whom Eternal Life is given! and with what Circumſpection is the way of Holineſs walked in, which ends in Life Everlaſting! <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 22, 23. Affliction awakens the Saints care, to improve Time, to <hi>work while 'tis day;</hi> for it will be <hi>too late</hi> to work, when the <hi>Night is once come;</hi> and how are they concerned, that there time be not ended, before Eternity be well provided for!</p>
            <p n="9">9. Another good Conſequent of Affliction, is <hi>Serious Diligence to make the Calling and Election ſure.</hi> When Affliction finds us at <hi>uncertainties</hi> in reference to our <hi>Spiritual State,</hi> our doubts and fears are amazing and tormenting. 'Tis ſad for a man to look upon himſelf as dying, and then to ſay,</p>
            <l>O animula vagula blandula,</l>
            <l>Quae nunc abibis in loca?</l>
            <p>
               <hi>O my Soul thou art departing hence, but whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, oh whither art thou going?</hi> What <hi>is like to be the place of thy Eternal abode, which muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be changed?</hi> To be <hi>dying</hi> and <hi>doubting</hi> at the ſame time is very ſad, though we are <hi>really</hi> never ſo ſafe. What is a well grounded Evidence of the Love of God in Chriſt, worth upon a bed of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? How valuable and comfortable the <hi>Spirits Teſtimony</hi> concerning our <hi>Adoption!</hi> Now Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction puts the Saints upon a more <hi>ſtrict</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Self-examination;</hi> and upon a more <hi>thorow</hi> and <hi>perceivable</hi> turning unto God, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43846:19"/> 39, 40. <hi>Wherefore, doth the living man complain, a man for the Puniſhment of his Sins? Let us ſearch and try our ways and turn unto the Lord our God.</hi> Affliction makes that Admonition of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to be heeded, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10, 11. <hi>Wherefore the rather Brethren give diligence to make your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election ſure; for if ye do theſe things ye ſhall never fall: For ſo an entrance ſhall be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to you abundantly into the Everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When once a Chriſtian has attained unto a <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance</hi> of the ſavour of God; how prepared is he for whatever may befall him! He can lie eaſie upon a Sick-bed; becauſe <hi>his God</hi> makes <hi>his Bed for him,</hi> Pſal. 41. 3. <hi>The Lord will ſtrengthen him upon the bed of Languiſhing; thou wilt make all his Bed in his Sickneſs.</hi> Nay the preſence of his God makes him fearleſs in the <hi>gloomy Valley</hi> of the <hi>Shadow of Death,</hi> Pſal. 23. 4. <hi>Though I walk through the Valley of the Shadow of Death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Another good Conſequent of Affliction, is <hi>ſpiritualized Affections, and a Converſation more in Heaven.</hi> Saints are caſt down by Affliction, that they may <hi>riſe</hi> with Chriſt and feel the <hi>Power of his Reſurrection more.</hi> That's a leſſon, which every Rod is ſent to teach, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Set your Affection on things above, and not on things which are upon the Earth.</hi> The harder the Ball is flung to the ground, it rebounds the higher; when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43846:20"/> God <hi>flings</hi> a Saint <hi>down</hi> with a <hi>mighty Hand,</hi> his Heart ſhould rebound higher towards Heaven, imitating thoſe excellent and faithful Ones; <hi>who confeſſed they were ſtrangers and Pilgrims on the Earth, who declared plainly they ſought a better Countrey,</hi> than any Countrey on Earth, becauſe they ſought an <hi>Heavenly Countrey.</hi> And <hi>God was not aſhamed to be called their God, for he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them a City.</hi> Heb. 11. 13, 16.</p>
            <p>The Pſalmiſt was very much helped towards Heaven by Chaſtiſement, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 14. <hi>All the day long</hi> (ſays he) <hi>have I been plagued, and chaſtned every Morning.</hi> And though for <hi>a while Temptation</hi> prevailed, yet at length his Thoughts and Eyes are fixed right, upon that <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> promiſed to ſuch as give up themſelves to God, and to be <hi>guided by his Counſel,</hi> V. 23. 24. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs I am continually with thee, thou haſt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den me by my right Hand. Thou ſhalt guide me with thy Counſel, and afterward receive me to Glory.</hi> Afflicted Saints ſtudy and endeavour to <hi>ſhew forth</hi> the <hi>Power and Vertue</hi> both of their Lord's <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Riſing again.</hi> How profitable is it to Dye, and to be Crucified with him! to be <hi>Dead to the World</hi> and <hi>all the Evil</hi> of it! And how Sweet and Pleaſant is it to <hi>riſe with him,</hi> and by <hi>earneſts</hi> and <hi>foretaſts</hi> of Glory to ſit <hi>with Him in Heavenly Places.</hi> Eph. 2. 4, 5, 6. <hi>But God who is Rich in Mercy for the great Love, wherewith he loved us, Even when we were dead in Sin hath quickned us together with Chriſt,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43846:20"/> 
               <hi>(by Grace ye are ſaved:) And hath raiſed us up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made us ſit together in Heavenly Places in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How great and good are theſe Conſequents, which follow upon Affliction!</p>
            <p>I come in the laſt Place to the <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhall begin with ſome <hi>Corollaries</hi> drawn from the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>If Saints are afflicted for their good,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence we may inferr, Afflictions are <hi>not Sings of Gods hatred,</hi> rather <hi>Tokens of his Love,</hi> They are the <hi>Lot of the Righteous.</hi> Pſal. 34. 19. <hi>Many are the Afflictions of the Righteous, but the Lord delivereth them</hi> at length <hi>out of them all.</hi> They are trained up under the Yoak; and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it well, is greatly beneficial. <hi>Man is born un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Trouble, as the ſparks fly upward.</hi> Troubles like ſparks of Fire are innumerable, which fill the few days of the Life of Man. But thoſe who are <hi>born again</hi> uſually have more troubles than other men. God cares for them, Hedges up their <hi>way with Thorns,</hi> which they may be afraid to <hi>break thorow;</hi> into <hi>Paths</hi> which are <hi>deſtructive.</hi> Hoſ. 2. 6. <hi>Therefore, behold I will Hedge up thy way with Thorns; and make a wall, that ſhe ſhall not find her Paths.</hi> Happy Saints in their Afflictions! who have both a <hi>Thorny Hedge,</hi> and alſo <hi>a wall</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43846:21"/> 
               <hi>between them,</hi> and the <hi>broad</hi> Road which leads unto Eternal Perdition!</p>
            <p>The Saints make an ill Comment upon their Afflictions, when they ſay, <hi>God cares not for them, nor how he deals with them.</hi> Several of them have <hi>born the Yoak in their Youth,</hi> and have ſtill <hi>carried it to their Graves.</hi> It is ſaid of <hi>One who lately died,</hi> that upon his Death-bed being asked, <hi>How long he had been ill?</hi> made this Reply, that he had been ill <hi>for fifty Years together.</hi> Chriſt was a <hi>Man of Sorrows,</hi> and yet the <hi>Son of Gods Love.</hi> You may be very much beloved of God, and yet be very much and often acquainted with griefs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saints in their Afflictions <hi>ſhould not be cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red becauſe afflicted.</hi> Holy <hi>Job,</hi> was ſtript na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and deprived of all that he had; and was ſmitten in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Perſon from Head to Foot; yet he was <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>eminently good,</hi> and under all theſe <hi>Evils</hi> held <hi>faſt his Righteouſneſs and Integrity.</hi> His Cenſorious Friends were blame-worthy in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him an Hypocrite, becauſe of his Sufferings. He had a greater underſtanding in the things of God, a ſounder Judgment, and more Grace in his Heart than they. The excellent young <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpake right indeed, when he pronounced <hi>Job,</hi> a man to be <hi>juſtified</hi> as to his State, <hi>Job</hi> 33. 32. But he blames him becauſe in vindicating himſelf, he ſpoke that, which <hi>too much reflected</hi> upon God himſelf, and therefore tells him, <hi>Job</hi> 34. 23. <hi>That God will not lay upon</hi> any <hi>Man,</hi> not upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43846:21"/> the beſt of Men, <hi>more than is Right, that he ſhould enter into Judgment with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as for the other three Friends of <hi>Job,</hi> who judged <hi>Job</hi> unſound in his Religion, becauſe of Gods heavy hand upon him; they are very ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebuked. The Lord owns his Servant whom they had ſo cenſured, <hi>Job</hi> 42. 7. <hi>The Lord ſaid to</hi> Eliphaz <hi>the</hi> Temanite, <hi>my Wrath is kindled againſt thee and againſt thy two Friends, for ye have not ſpoken of me the thing that is Right, as my Servant</hi> Job. And they are commanded to make uſe of <hi>Job</hi> as an Interceſſour for them, that they <hi>might not be dealt with according to their Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> To <hi>cenſure</hi> a Saint is <hi>ill,</hi> but to cenſure him <hi>in Affliction,</hi> and <hi>only becauſe of Affliction</hi> is <hi>worſe,</hi> becauſe this <hi>adds</hi> ſo much to his Affliction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is <hi>no ground or reaſon for impatience in the Saints, whatever Afflictions are their Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</hi> It may be a check to impatience, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the very <hi>beſt</hi> have deſerved <hi>worſe a thouſand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold,</hi> than ever they have ſuffered, but the moſt effectual Remedy againſt Impatience, is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Profit of Affliction. Why ſhould Saints repine and murmur at that which is ſo good for them? When their Father is humbling, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, and healing of them; when he is carrying on the good Work begun in them, towards great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Perfection; why ſhould they count themſelves hardly dealt with? The <hi>Father of Spirits,</hi> is not like the <hi>Fathers of our Fleſh,</hi> Will and Humour
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43846:22"/> appears in <hi>their</hi> Corrections; but He gives not a <hi>blow,</hi> but what is for his <hi>Childrens Profit.</hi> Heb. 12. 10. And why ſhould any be impatient at their being Profited and Advantaged? Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the bleſſed iſſue of the Saints Troubles; they ſhould be born with <hi>all thankfulneſs;</hi> for ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Afflictions are <hi>great Promotions,</hi> and hereby <hi>mighty advances</hi> are made in <hi>Heavens way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis unreaſonable for the Saints, <hi>becauſe of their Afflictions to queſtion Divine Providence, or to conclude that Religion is vain.</hi> The Pſalmiſt under the <hi>Rod</hi> and <hi>Temptation</hi> together, was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to draw ſuch Concluſions. <hi>Continued chast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> made him to <hi>think of God,</hi> and <hi>to ſpeak</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion unbecomingly</hi> and indeed <hi>impiouſly.</hi> He was ſo <hi>foiled</hi> by the Tempter, <hi>that his Feet were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt gone;</hi> and 'twas hard for him to recover; ſtrange kind of Language he utters, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Therefore his People return hither, and Waters of a full Cup are wrung out to them. And they ſay how doth God know, and is there Knowledge in the moſt high? Behold theſe are the ungodly, who proſper in the World, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in Riches; Verily I have cleanſed my Heart in vain and waſht my hands in Innocency; for all the day long have I been plagued and chaſtned every Morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at length the Pſalmiſt <hi>comes to himſelf,</hi> V. 15. <hi>If I ſay, I will ſpeak thus: behold I ſhould offend againſt the Generation of thy Children.</hi> And
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43846:22"/> he gives himſelf <hi>very bad Words,</hi> but ſuch as his yielding ſo far to that Temptation <hi>very well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> V. 21, 22. <hi>Thus my Heart was grieved, and I was pricked in my Reins, ſo fooliſh was I and ignorant: I was as a beaſt before thee.</hi> But he is <hi>cured</hi> of his <hi>brutiſhneſs,</hi> and ſpeaks like a Saint, expreſſing <hi>deſires after God</hi> above <hi>all things in Heaven and Earth;</hi> concludes it <hi>good to draw near</hi> to God, and <hi>rejoices</hi> in him as the <hi>Strength of his Heart</hi> and his <hi>Portion for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Saint never ſo much afflicted; yet to <hi>be,</hi> and <hi>continue</hi> a Saint, is certainly <hi>good</hi> for him, and a <hi>wiſe part</hi> in him. <hi>Job</hi> when ſitting upon the ground <hi>among the Aſhes,</hi> full <hi>of Boyls,</hi> and <hi>Scraping himſelf with a Potſheard,</hi> was ſtill dear to God. And ſo was <hi>Lazarus lying at the Rich mans</hi> Gate; deſiring to be fed <hi>with the Crumbs which fell from the Rich mans Table.</hi> Saints under the greateſt Troubles <hi>can't be miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> for <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Theirs,</hi> and <hi>They</hi> are <hi>His</hi> ſtill; and theſe very Troubles do promote their Holineſs and their Happineſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Proſperity of the Wicked, and their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from Affliction, ſhould not raiſe the Saints Envy.</hi> Saints are frequently tempted to envy the wicked their good things, and ſometimes <hi>this Envy has prevailed,</hi> and has been their fault and failing; it has proved their great both <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Torment, Pſal.</hi> 73. 3. <hi>I was Envious at the Fooliſh, when I ſaw the Proſperity of the Wiched.</hi> That Caution
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43846:23"/> is but needful, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 1. <hi>Fret not thy ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of evil doers, neither be thou envious at the Workers of Iniquity.</hi> For a man that is made <hi>wiſe to Salvation,</hi> to be envious at the <hi>Fooliſh;</hi> for a man that is <hi>enriched with Grace,</hi> to be envious at the <hi>Workers of Iniquity,</hi> becauſe of their Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; there is <hi>no Reaſon</hi> at all for it. Alas! this Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of theirs is greatly to their <hi>Prejudice,</hi> and helps forward their Perdition, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 32. <hi>The turning away</hi> or the <hi>eaſe</hi> of the <hi>ſimple ſhall ſlay them, and the Proſperity of Fools ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> And this Deſtruction is <hi>haſtning,</hi> and comes <hi>unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly, ſuddenly,</hi> and ſo the more <hi>unavoidably</hi> upon them, and 'twil be <hi>utter</hi> and <hi>Eternal</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 17, 18, 19. <hi>Until I went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sanctuary of God, then underſtood I their End. Surely thou didſt ſet them in ſlippery places, thou caſteſt them down into Deſtruction: How are they brought into Deſolation as in a Moment, they are utterly conſumed with terrours!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greateſt Wealth and Glory of the Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; conſidering how <hi>ſoon 'twill end,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> will <hi>follow when it ends;</hi> ſhould not <hi>ſtir our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> but rather our <hi>Pitty and Compaſſion;</hi> for they walk in a <hi>vain ſhew</hi> full of <hi>vain Confidence,</hi> till their <hi>Feet go down to Death; and their ſteps take hold of Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. To be <hi>Incorrigible under Affliction is inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable.</hi> As 'tis good for Saints to be afflicted, ſo all <hi>ſhould</hi> be <hi>bettered</hi> by Affliction. 'Tis a great
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43846:23"/> Aggravation of Sin to <hi>ſmart</hi> and <hi>bleed</hi> and <hi>groan,</hi> becauſe of it, and yet <hi>ſtill to Love</hi> it. If Saints are afflicted for their Good; when <hi>Sinners</hi> are <hi>afflicted,</hi> a <hi>great price</hi> is put into their hands, which may be improved to an Eternal Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. In Proſperity, the Ungodly are uſually hardned in Pride and Earthlineſs, and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Senſuality; the Lord not rebuking them, nor <hi>preſently executing Sentence againſt their Evil Works,</hi> they are apt <hi>to think</hi> Him <hi>altogether ſuch an one as themſelves.</hi> Pſal. 50. 21. and that <hi>he diſlikes</hi> Sin no more than <hi>they</hi> do. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>their Hearts are fully ſet in them to do Evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 8. 11.</p>
            <p>But when wicked Ones are viſited with Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and they feel the ſmart of the Rod; God is really very near them; and if they would but cry to him with their Hearts; how readily would he hear and turn them to himſelf, and turn his anger away from them! <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 18. <hi>I have ſurely heard</hi> Ephraim <hi>bemoaning himſelf thus; Thou haſt chaſtiſed me, and I was chaſtiſed; as a Bullock un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accuſtomed to the Yoak; turn thou me and I ſhall be turned, for thou art the Lord my God.</hi> And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deſire, he was <hi>turned</hi> and <hi>inſtructed,</hi> he obtained ſure Mercy, and became a <hi>dear Son,</hi> a <hi>pleaſant Child,</hi> notwithſtanding all his former foul Sins and <hi>reproachful Abominations,</hi> V. 19, 20. But when Sinners are ſmitten in vain; and receive no Correction: Nay like <hi>Ahaz</hi> in their Affliction <hi>treſpaſs yet more;</hi> this Argues <hi>a great Love to Sin:</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:43846:24"/> and the <hi>more</hi> provokes the Lord to <hi>Jealouſie and Indignation. Judah</hi> was ſtrangely fond of, and wedded to their Idolatry and other Wickedneſs, when the <hi>Soreſt Judgments</hi> could not be a <hi>means to divorce</hi> them from it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. 3. <hi>O Lord are not thine Eyes upon the Truth? Thou haſt ſmitten them, but they have not grieved, thou haſt conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, but they have refuſed to receive Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, they have made their Faces harder than a Rock, they have refuſed to return.</hi> 'Tis the <hi>highth</hi> of <hi>Madneſs</hi> to be <hi>Sins Martyrs,</hi> and not only to ſuffer trouble in this World; but for the ſake of it, to <hi>venture burning</hi> in Hell for evermore!</p>
            <p n="7">7. How great is <hi>the goodneſs of God, who can make the Evil of Affliction to Work for good to his People!</hi> 'Tis the Phyſicians great art ſo to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Poyſon, as to turn it into a powerful and wholeſom Medicine. What is <hi>Evil</hi> in it <hi>ſelf,</hi> and evil, and <hi>Deſtructive to Nature,</hi> God does make it become <hi>very good</hi> to the Saints, and to <hi>further the work of Grace</hi> in them. How ſecurely may ſuch a Gracious God be relied on! who can make the <hi>worſt things,</hi> a Saint meets with in this World, to prove <hi>Helps and Advantages!</hi> This goodneſs of God is firmly to be believed, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and confided in; and conſidering the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and freeneſs of it, too much cannot be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from it. Much of it is manifeſted, and <hi>laid out</hi> at preſent, and <hi>much more is laid up</hi> for the Saints in the other World, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. 19. <hi>Oh how great is thy goodneſs which thou haſt laid up for</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43846:24"/> 
               <hi>them that fear thee, which thou haſt wrought for them that truſt in thee, before the Sons of Men!</hi> If the goodneſs of God turns <hi>Evil</hi> into <hi>Good;</hi> what may be expected from the <hi>good things</hi> he gives his People! how <hi>much good ſhall they do them!</hi> how beneficial ſhall the <hi>Miniſtry of the Word,</hi> Holy <hi>Ordinances;</hi> and the <hi>Priviledges of the Sanctuary</hi> prove to the Saints! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. 4. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chooſeſt, and cauſeſt to approach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that he may dwell in thy Courts; we ſhall be ſatisfied with the goodneſs of thy Houſe even of thy Holy Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Saints are <hi>exceedingly culpable and to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when after Affliction they decline, inſtead of growing better.</hi> It argues Corruption very ſtrong when Affliction does not purge it out. <hi>Folly</hi> is but <hi>too faſt bound up</hi> in the Heart; that the <hi>Rod of God</hi> does not <hi>drive it</hi> away. Gods <hi>Love</hi> is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with <hi>Jealouſie;</hi> let Saints therefore <hi>be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of themſelves,</hi> leſt after Affliction their Hearts deal treacherouſly and prove unſtedfaſt.</p>
            <p>Good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was <hi>Sick,</hi> and had the <hi>Sentence of Death</hi> pronounced upon him; but he falls a <hi>praying hard,</hi> and <hi>weeping ſore;</hi> his Tears <hi>deörſum fluunt, ſed coelum petunt,</hi> fell to the Ground, but Heaven is affected at ſhedding of them. He is <hi>heard,</hi> he is <hi>ſpared,</hi> he is <hi>healed;</hi> and <hi>brought into the Houſe of God,</hi> when he expected to have <hi>been carried to the Grave.</hi> And ſuch a <hi>Sign</hi> was given him, to aſſure him of going to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43846:25"/> as amazed the World, the <hi>Sun</hi> in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament went ſo <hi>many degrees backward.</hi> Now how much <hi>Faith, Humility, Gratitude, Obedience,</hi> might have been <hi>expected</hi> from ſo <hi>good a man,</hi> to whom ſuch ſingular goodneſs had been manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted! But Alas! <hi>Hezekiah rendred not again ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Benefit done to him, for his Heart was lifted up; therefore there was wrath upon him, and upon</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32. 25. His <hi>Riches and Honour,</hi> which he had in <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> might puff him up; and the thought of that <hi>Sign,</hi> which declared him a <hi>ſpecial favourite of Heaven,</hi> as he ſuppoſed; unto the <hi>King of</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, might alſo make his Heart to <hi>ſwell</hi> within him.</p>
            <p>No Saint that is Wiſe, will be Self-confident; for after the removal of Affliction, there is great danger of Security and Backſliding; Self-jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie therefore, and a ſenſe of natural impotency, and unfaithfulneſs to our ſelves, ſhould make us cry to be <hi>upheld by Him,</hi> who is of <hi>Power to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh us.</hi> If Saints <hi>receive not Correction;</hi> how ſoon may they be <hi>taken in hand</hi> and <hi>again laſhed!</hi> And their not profiting by the Rod, fills <hi>Satans Mouth</hi> with <hi>Accuſations</hi> againſt them; and their own <hi>Conſciences</hi> with <hi>Reproaches;</hi> Gods <hi>diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> grows <hi>hotter,</hi> and more <hi>ſmarting blows</hi> may be expected, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. 23. 24. <hi>And if ye will not be reformed by me by theſe things, but will walk contrary unto me; then will I alſo walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto you, and will puniſh you yet ſeven times for your Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:43846:25"/>
            <p> USE II. Of Advice to more <hi>Notorious Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> whoſe ſcandalous Lives witneſs to the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their State; and by their conſtant <hi>Evil Works</hi> they ſhew they are <hi>Children that have no Faith;</hi> or if their Sin be not ſo apparent to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, 'tis apparent to themſelves; Conſcience, if they would but heed it; charges them with <hi>ſecret wickedneſs,</hi> which is committed with great <hi>Preſumption and Boldneſs.</hi> If ſuch as theſe, are ſeized upon by <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> or feel any other ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rod; I would give them ſuch Advice, as if it be followed, their Affliction will have a good iſſue and effect upon them, as bad as they are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When Affliction overtakes you, that are very wicked; <hi>Take notice how your Sin has found you out.</hi> That threatning, <hi>Num.</hi> 32. 23. is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed. <hi>Ye have ſinn'd againſt the Lord, and be ſure your Sin will find you out.</hi> It has been <hi>hunting</hi> you, with <hi>Evils</hi> at the <hi>heels</hi> of it; and now it has actually overtaken you. You dream't not of this in the hour of Temptation, when Sin was repreſented to you by your ſubtle Enemy, as <hi>all Gain and Pleaſure;</hi> Affliction ſhews the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it has brought you to; and that 'tis full of Gall and Wormwood. Thus Sin found out <hi>Judah</hi> of old, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>Thine own wickedneſs ſhall correct thee, and thy backſlidings ſhall reprove thee; know therefore and ſee that it is an evil thing and bitter, that thou haſt forſaken the Lord thy God, and that my fear is not in thee, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts.</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43846:26"/> Sin <hi>your Enemy</hi> has <hi>found</hi> you; and you feel to your Coſt and Wo, that it is an Enemy indeed. <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> was once <hi>ſweet in your Mouths,</hi> and you did <hi>hide it under your Tongue;</hi> you <hi>ſpared it</hi> and would by no means <hi>forſake it;</hi> but now in your <hi>Bowels 'tis turned,</hi> and is the <hi>very Gall of Aſps within you,</hi> Job 20. 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Behold you that are wicked, <hi>how God is come forth in anger againſt you;</hi> there is a Rod in his hand, frowns in his face; and he is full of juſt Indignation againſt you. And who <hi>can ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Indignation?</hi> Nah. 1. 2. <hi>God is Jealous, and the Lord Revengeth; the Lord Revengeth and is furious; the Lord will take Vengeance on his Adverſaries, and reſerveth wrath for his Enemies.</hi> Such <hi>Potſheards</hi> of the Earth as, the ſtrongeſt and ſtouteſt Sinners of you all, are; cannot ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>your Maker,</hi> when he is Contending with you, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 14. <hi>Can thy Heart endure, or can thy hands be ſtrong, when I ſhall deal with thee?</hi> If the <hi>Wrath of a King,</hi> be as the <hi>Meſſenger of Death:</hi> What is the anger of Him, <hi>who is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> who does <hi>what he will, in the Army of Heaven and among the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth, and none can ſtay his hand, or ſay to him, What doſt thou? ſince all the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the World are reputed as nothing before him,</hi> Dan. 4. 35.</p>
            <p>This Anger of God has Almighty and Irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Strength joined with it, and therefore 'tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43846:26"/> terrible, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 11. <hi>Who knows the Power of thine Anger? even according to thy Fear, ſo is thy Wrath.</hi> Though there be never ſo much fear and dread of God in the Hearts of any; the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God, if ready to fall upon them, deſerves all that fear; the <hi>Devils believe</hi> and feel this wrath, and are apprehenſive of its continuance and increaſe, therefore <hi>they tremble,</hi> Jam. 2. 20. See O Sinner, that the glorious and dreadful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of Heaven and Earth, is angry with <hi>Thee in Particular.</hi> Thou <hi>art the man,</hi> who haſt <hi>bitterly provoked</hi> him. <hi>Thy Iniquities are hateful to him.</hi> Now if God is not at all taken notice of; if his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is not at all minded; nor any courſe or care ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to appeaſe it; it will be blown up to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er fierceneſs, and this fire may quickly devour, conſume; and having begun with thee, make a ſpeedy and utter end of thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It concerns you to <hi>fear Him, under whoſe Power you are,</hi> and who is able to deſtroy <hi>both the Body and the Soul</hi> likewiſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 4, 5. <hi>And I ſay unto you my Friends, Be not afraid of them, that kill the Body, and after that have no more that they can do; But I will forewarn you, whom you ſhall fear; fear him who after he hath killed, hath Power to caſt into Hell, yea, I ſay unto you, fear him.</hi> His hands did make that <hi>Earthly Houſe</hi> of your Tabernacle; and he can bring it <hi>to the duſt again.</hi> Your Souls, he can require when be pleaſes, and if you dye in your Sins, your Souls will be doom'd to the place, where other damned
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43846:27"/> Spirits are; and they are loſt beyond all hopes and poſſibility of recovery. Oh! <hi>ſanctifie the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> in <hi>whoſe hand</hi> you <hi>are, under whoſe hand</hi> you <hi>groan;</hi> by <hi>making him your fear and dread;</hi> he can command both <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond death</hi> to ſeize on you, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 8. <hi>And I looked and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a Pale Horſe, and his Name that ſate on him was Death, and Hell followed with him.</hi> Death is the <hi>King of Terrors,</hi> but <hi>Hell</hi> is ten thouſand times <hi>more terrible.</hi> Oh! be afraid of that mighty hand, which with <hi>one blow</hi> can both <hi>kill and damn</hi> you together. You cannot ſecure your ſelves by <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> by <hi>Flight,</hi> or by <hi>Reſiſtance;</hi> for Gods <hi>Eye is all-ſeeing,</hi> his Power and Hand is irreſiſtible, and extends it ſelf, all <hi>Heaven and Earth and Hell over;</hi> therefore humbling your ſelves, and Submiſſion, would be the beſt and wiſeſt way that you can take.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In this ill Caſe in which you are, <hi>remember now your evil ways, and your doings that have not been good,</hi> Ezek. 36. 31. <hi>Then ſhall ye remember your evil ways, and your doings that were not good, and ſhall loath your ſelves in your own ſight for your Iniquities and Abominations.</hi> Your remembring of your Tranſgreſſions, is one way to have God forget them; loath your ſelves, and he will not loath you; condemning your ſelves, is the way not to be condemned by him. <hi>Humble your ſelves in the ſight of the Lord, and he will lift you up,</hi> Jam. 4. 10. Oh ſmite upon your thighs and ſay, <hi>What have we done?</hi> How <hi>manifold</hi> are our Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions! How <hi>mighty</hi> are our Sins! What <hi>guilt</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:43846:27"/> have we incurr'd! How <hi>monſtrouſly black and foul</hi> are our <hi>Defilements!</hi> What <hi>wrath</hi> have we provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked! How <hi>hot and low</hi> a place in Hell have we <hi>deſerved!</hi> Innumerable <hi>Evils compaſs us about; our Iniquities have taken hold upon us, ſo that we are not able to look up; they are more than the Hairs of our Heads, therefore our Hearts fail us.</hi> Pſal. 40. 12. See how <hi>deceitful polluting</hi> and <hi>damnable</hi> the Nature of Sin is; call your ſelves by the right Name, <hi>Fools; foes to your ſelves; Self-murtherers and Self-deſtroyers;</hi> in giving way to Iniquity. Be utterly <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> with your ſelves for ſinning againſt God, and wronging your own Souls; and <hi>fall out</hi> with <hi>all ſin</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Be <hi>Inquiſitive what you muſt do to be ſaved?</hi> You that are <hi>outwardly afflicted,</hi> and alſo <hi>prickt in the Heart,</hi> and <hi>wounded in your Conſciences;</hi> ſhould very ſeriouſly inquire whether the <hi>door of Hope</hi> be not <hi>yet open</hi> to you, and what courſe you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> muſt take to be <hi>ſaved from Sin and Wrath,</hi> and to have your <hi>Peace with God made.</hi> Indeed the Lord ſpeaks confoundingly and terribly to wicked men in their Calamity, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>I will laugh at your Calamity, and will mock when your fear cometh; when your fear cometh as Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Deſtruction as a Whirlwind, when Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs and Anguiſh cometh upon you; then ſhall they call upon me, but I will not Anſwer: They ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not find me: for that they hated Knowledg, and did not chuſe the fear of the Lord.</hi> And do you acknowledge that the Lord
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43846:28"/> might juſtly ſpeak ſuch Language to <hi>you;</hi> but withal know, that theſe diſtreſſed Sinners, had theſe <hi>cries extorted</hi> from them <hi>meerly</hi> by Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but had <hi>no deſire</hi> to be <hi>turned from their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</hi> Therefore you that are brought very low by Affliction; do not only cry to God to <hi>deliver you</hi> from your trouble; but that he <hi>would alſo purge away your Sins for his Name ſake.</hi> Pſal. 79. 9. And let not your Diſconſolate Spirits doubt; for <hi>there is hope</hi> in <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 7, 8. <hi>Let</hi> Iſrael <hi>hope in the Lord, for with the Lord there is Mercy, and with him is plenteous Redemption, and he will redeem</hi> Iſrael <hi>from all his Iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Look upon God as <hi>acceſſible, and reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in a Mediator, who is his beloved Son the Lord Jeſus. Chriſt has ſuffered once for Sins, the juſt for the unjuſt that he might bring men to God,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 18. <hi>And God is in Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling the World to himſelf, not imputing their Treſpaſſes to them,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 19. <hi>Now then,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us, we pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye reconciled to God.</hi> God is <hi>more forward</hi> to be at Peace with you, then <hi>you are aware.</hi> He <hi>intreats</hi> you to accept of that <hi>Pardon,</hi> which you deſire, and ſo much need, but <hi>fear you ſhall not obtain;</hi> and if you value his favour in Chriſt, and intreat it with your whole Heart; you ſhall <hi>not die</hi> under his <hi>Diſpleaſure, Pſal.</hi> 119. 58. <hi>I intreated thy favour with my</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:43846:28"/> 
               <hi>whole Heart; be merciful to me according to thy Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are you willing upon <hi>any terms</hi> to have the breach made up between God and you? Do you conſent to <hi>be</hi> any thing, to <hi>do</hi> any thing, to <hi>part with</hi> any thing which he would have you; ſo <hi>you</hi> may be but <hi>His,</hi> and <hi>He Yours;</hi> a God in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with you; and a Father to you? Then let your drooping Hearts revive, for <hi>there is an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, who is the Propitiation for the Sins of the whole World,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 1, 2. His <hi>Blood ſpeaks better things than that of</hi> Abel; cries louder for Mercy, than your Sin can cry for Vengeance. Here you may <hi>ſafely venture your Faith,</hi> for Chriſts Blood is the Blood of him, <hi>who is God</hi> as well as man; and he is able to reconcile God and Men together, and thoſe men who have been never ſo much <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enated and Enemies in their Minds by Reaſon of wicked Works,</hi> Col. 1. 21. In your Affliction be ſenſible of Gods anger; and readily grant the juſtneſs of it; but do not look upon if, as <hi>not to be appeaſed.</hi> If you come to him by Jeſus Chriſt, you will find his Fury all gone, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 4, 5. <hi>Fury is not in me; let him take hold of my Strength, that he may make Peace with me, and he ſhall make Peace with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Pray to be <hi>turned from Sin it ſelf; as well as have the afflicting hand of God removed.</hi> 'Tis an ill thing <hi>to chuſe Iniquity rather than Affliction,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:43846:29"/> Job 36. 21. Many under Sickneſs, cry to have <hi>bodily Health</hi> reſtored, but the Diſeaſes of their Souls they feel not; neither is the <hi>health of the Soul</hi> valued. Many a man in Affliction and Pain, does call upon God, ſaying, <hi>Lord heal my Body!</hi> but he was a man after Gods own Heart, who ſaid, <hi>Lord be merciful to me, heal my Soul for I have ſinned againſt thee,</hi> Pſal. 41. 4. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> cried to be delivered from the <hi>Plagues of</hi> Egypt; but not from the <hi>hardneſs</hi> of his Heart, neither did he deſire to fear the Name of God; if he had: both his Drowning and Damnation might have been prevented. You who are afflicted, I grant, may pray for the <hi>ſparing of your Lives;</hi> with Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Will of God; and that <hi>his ſtroke may be removed</hi> away from you. The Pſalmiſt prays for both, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 10, 13. <hi>Remove thy ſtroke away from me, I am conſumed by the blow of thy hand. O ſpare me, that I may recover Strength before I go away from hence, and be no more:</hi> But before, he had prayed, that he might be <hi>delivered from Sin;</hi> for this was the greateſt Evil, <hi>Ver.</hi> 7, 8. <hi>And now Lord what wait I for? my Hope is in Thee; deliver me from all my Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</hi> This he Hopes, this he Longs, this he Waits upon God for; that he might be deliver'd from his Tranſgreſſions, not <hi>ſome</hi> only but from <hi>all</hi> of them, that neither the <hi>guilt of Sin</hi> might <hi>lie</hi> upon him, nor <hi>any Iniquity</hi> have the <hi>Dominion</hi> over him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>You that have lived wickedly, and God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43846:29"/> of you with the blows of his hand; have great cauſe to be <hi>Self-ſuſpicious</hi> leaſt all your <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and <hi>Devotion at preſent,</hi> be onely <hi>forced;</hi> by what you <hi>feel</hi> and <hi>fear:</hi> You had need there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to beg that a <hi>thorow</hi> and <hi>laſting change</hi> may be wrought in your Hearts, or elſe your <hi>hot fit</hi> of Religion will quickly be off; <hi>Your goodneſs will be as the Morning Cloud, and as the early Dew, ſo it will go away,</hi> Hoſ. 6. 4. Oh cry for the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying Spirit, that he may <hi>dwell in</hi> you <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally;</hi> and <hi>Conſecrate you as Temples,</hi> for himſelf to abide in; and <hi>cauſe</hi> you to walk in the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Ways</hi> of the Lord unto the very end.</p>
            <p>And if You that are Notorious Sinners are ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and God does <hi>ſend his Word and heal you,</hi> and deliver you from the <hi>Pit of Deſtruction.</hi> I would farther adviſe you in theſe following par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Think with your ſelves, if <hi>Affliction had carried you off in your Sins</hi> into another World; whither Oh! whither had you gone? At Death all Souls are diſpoſed of in the place which they are <hi>fit</hi> for. Holy Souls are made <hi>meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light,</hi> and when ſeparated from the Body, they enter upon that Inheritance. The Souls of the Wicked were continually <hi>fitting themſelves for Deſtruction;</hi> at Death they are <hi>ripe</hi> for it, and are <hi>thrown</hi> into it. The Wicked who die in their Sins, what a woful place are they turned into! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 17.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43846:30"/> 
               <hi>The Wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and all the Nations that forget God.</hi> That Rich and ſenſual <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> who called <hi>Abraham Father,</hi> but choſe the Pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon, before Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Life Eternal; what became of him? After Death, the next News we hear of him was this; He <hi>was in Hell,</hi> he <hi>ſees Heaven afar off, too far</hi> for him <hi>ever to Hope</hi> to <hi>come thither.</hi> He ſaw too late, what he had miſt of; and how <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>unquenchable</hi> were the <hi>Flames</hi> in which he was tormented! <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 23, 24. On! Sinner, if thon hadſt died in thy Wickedneſs and Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt God, thou hadſt been dealt withal as an Enemy, ſent away with a Curſe into Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Fire; without Hopes of Reconciliation or Releaſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Admire the <hi>Patience and Goodneſs of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you.</hi> You burthen'd him with your Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, 'tis a wonder he did not eaſe himſelf of the Load; that, that Word did not take hold of you, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 24. <hi>Ah! I will eaſe me of my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and avenge me of my Enemies.</hi> He might have glorified his Righteouſneſs, Purity, Power, and Truth, in your juſt Condemnation and Miſery; but he has pittied and ſpared you; and <hi>ſtill waits to be Graoious.</hi> Now do not ſhew your ſelves <hi>ſuch rebels,</hi> as neither <hi>Severity</hi> nor <hi>Goodneſs</hi> will <hi>overcome,</hi> as neither <hi>fair</hi> means, nor <hi>foul</hi> will <hi>work upon</hi> and <hi>better.</hi> Do not Act, as if you were <hi>delivered to work Abomination.</hi> Though the Patience of God be wonderful, yet
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43846:30"/>
'tis not <hi>Eternal,</hi> and when <hi>abuſing</hi> it, brings it to <hi>an end;</hi> the following <hi>Fury</hi> is dreadful to the <hi>Abuſers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Remember, the <hi>Sparing of you is owing to the Lord Jeſus.</hi> He interceeds that the <hi>fruitleſs Fig-tree may be ſpared,</hi> and <hi>tried</hi> a little longer; and how <hi>well</hi> will it be, if at length it bring forth fruit which is good. Whatever Deliverances and Salvation wicked men partake of; Chriſt is the Author of them, for he is affirmed to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Saviour of all men, though <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> eſpecially of them that believe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 10. And as the Lord Redeemer has interceded for your ſparing, ſo he offers a <hi>far greater Benefit if</hi> you <hi>will accept it;</hi> to <hi>make Peace</hi> for you, to work <hi>true Grace</hi> in you, to <hi>Open your Eyes and to turn you from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan to God, that you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive forgiveneſs of Sins, and an Inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that are Sanctified by Faith which is in Him.</hi> Act. 26. 18.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be ſure to Sin <hi>no more Preſumptuouſly, leaſt a worſe thing come next,</hi> Joh. 5. 14. Jeſus found the man whom he had healed <hi>in the Temple,</hi> a <hi>proper place,</hi> after his <hi>recovery</hi> to be found in, and he ſaith to him. <hi>Behold, thou art made whole, Sin no more, leaſt a worſe thing come to thee.</hi> If after the return of health, and the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of the Rod. you <hi>turn away from the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment delivered to you; and it happens to you</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:43846:31"/> 
               <hi>according to the Proverb, The Dog is turned to his own vomit again, and the Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the Mire.</hi> You becoming <hi>worſe than ever,</hi> and more <hi>inexcuſable than ever</hi> in being ſo; <hi>worſe than ever</hi> from <hi>Gods hand</hi> is to be expected. Greater Diſtreſs may quickly ſeize you; and the <hi>loudeſt cries</hi> may have a <hi>deaf Ear</hi> turned to them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 41. <hi>They cried but there was none to ſave, even to the Lord, but he anſwered them not.</hi> That may be the Lords Determination concerning you, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. 18. <hi>Therefore will I alſo deal in fury, mine Eye ſhall not ſpare, neither will I have pitty, and though they cry in my Ears with a loud voice, yet will I not hear them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though Gods hand be off from you, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he can quickly lay it on again; and it may be ſo heavy, as to make you fall under it. See what is threatned to the tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>And now alſo the Ax is laid to the Root of the Trees, therefore every Tree, which bringeth not forth good Fruit is hewen down and caſt into the Fire:</hi> And if this bringing forth <hi>no good Fruit</hi> brings the Tree to <hi>Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burning,</hi> what <hi>fierce Flames,</hi> will <hi>burn</hi> thoſe Trees, which bring forth a <hi>great deal of bad Fruit?</hi> Such as you read of, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 32, 33. <hi>For their Vine is of the Vine of</hi> Sodom, <hi>and of the Fields of</hi> Gomorrah; <hi>their Grapes are Grapes of Gall, their Cluſters are bitter, their Wine is the Poyſon of Dragons, and the cruel Venom of Aſps.</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:43846:31"/> To go on in Sin, after recovery from Sickneſs may ſhorten your days, and make <hi>Sentence againſt you to be ſpeedily executed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Though <hi>Death is a little delayed, yet it will certainly and quickly come;</hi> let it not <hi>find you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared.</hi> Heb. 9. 27. <hi>It is appointed unto men once to dye; and after this the Judgment.</hi> And this appointment is concerning <hi>you,</hi> as well as others. Therefore ſpeak every one of you, as <hi>Job</hi> did, <hi>Job</hi> 30. 23. <hi>For I know that thou wilt bring me to Death, and to the Houſe appointed for all the living.</hi> 'Tis not more certain you <hi>are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,</hi> than 'tis certain, that you <hi>ſhall ſhortly die.</hi> And wo to you if you <hi>lie ſtill,</hi> and at laſt <hi>die</hi> in your <hi>Wickedneſs.</hi> If <hi>Sin</hi> be the <hi>ſting of Death,</hi> then ſo <hi>many Sins</hi> as you have been guilty of, ſo <hi>many ſtings</hi> will <hi>your Death</hi> have. A <hi>King of Terrors</hi> indeed it will be found; when with ſo many ſtings 'tis <hi>armed!</hi> Pray hard that a <hi>ſaving change</hi> may be wrought <hi>in Heart and Life,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>great change</hi> come; and that you may <hi>paſs from Death to Life</hi> in a <hi>Spiritual Senſe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a <hi>Natural Senſe</hi> you paſs from Life to <hi>Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE III. Of <hi>Direction</hi> more <hi>generally unto all;</hi> and here I ſhall direct you,</p>
            <p>How to carry it <hi>under Affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:43846:32"/>
            <p> And likewiſe how <hi>after Affliction;</hi> that you may receive much good by Affliction.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, I am to direct you, how to carry it under Affliction.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Under Affliction <hi>be perſwaded and take great notice that</hi> God himſelf <hi>is come to viſit you.</hi> Though he be not the Author of ſin, yet <hi>Penal Evils</hi> are <hi>all</hi> from him; chaſtning is called the <hi>Chaſtning of the Lord,</hi> Heb. 12. 5. Chaſtiſements are ſtiled <hi>his rebukes.</hi> His Providence is ſo exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, that not a <hi>Sparrow falls to the ground with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Him.</hi> Nothing then befalls any of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men; but by Divine Appointment. Fix your Eyes therefore upon God. He has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken you in hand, and out of his hand none can reſcue you; and the <hi>wound</hi> that is made, will remain uncured; till the <hi>ſame</hi> hand <hi>heal,</hi> which <hi>gave</hi> it, <hi>Job</hi> 9 13. <hi>If God will not withdraw his anger, the Proud helpers do ſtoop under him.</hi> The <hi>Chaldeans</hi> were the <hi>Ax;</hi> but Gods hand <hi>hewed Iſrael</hi> with it; they were the <hi>Saw,</hi> but Gods hand did <hi>ſhake</hi> it. And when you ſee, 'tis really God himſelf that viſits you in Severity; behave your ſelves as <hi>Creatures ought</hi> to do towards their <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;</hi> who is infinitely <hi>above</hi> them; has been <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended</hi> by them; can eaſily <hi>cruſh</hi> them; and yet is able and ready upon Humiliation to <hi>cure</hi> them.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:43846:32"/>
            <p> If the <hi>Inviſible God,</hi> who corrects, were more eyed, in all the ſtrokes he give, you; this would have a mighty Efficacy to <hi>abaſe</hi> you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and to make Affliction <hi>attain</hi> its <hi>end</hi> upon you, that an <hi>end might be put</hi> to your Affliction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Under Affliction, <hi>Juſtifie God, and accept the Puniſhment of your Iniquity;</hi> in Affliction <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> may ſpeak very <hi>plain and home,</hi> and ſo as that you have nothing to reply; and the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> may ſet in with Conſcience, and make its <hi>charge</hi> more <hi>unanſwerable.</hi> Heedfully liſten to Conſcience, and Mind the <hi>Convictions</hi> of the Spirit. <hi>Oh ſearch and try your ways,</hi> the ways that your <hi>Hearts and Affections</hi> have gone; as well as the Paths you have broken with <hi>your Feet.</hi> Be better acquainted with the <hi>evil nature</hi> of your own ways, and their pernicious and deſtructive Tendency. Lay <hi>blame</hi> where it <hi>ought</hi> to be laid, upon an <hi>evil Heart</hi> eſpecially; for that's the fruitful womb, in which Sin is <hi>conceived,</hi> that <hi>brings forth</hi> all the Evils, wherewith the <hi>man is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed.</hi> 'Tis the Evil Heart, which <hi>through unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief departs from the Living God;</hi> and is inclined to <hi>dead works, and lying Vanities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fail not to <hi>clear the Juſtice of God,</hi> as it is written, <hi>That thou mighteſt be juſtified in thy ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and mighteſt overcome, when thou art judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Rom. 3. 4. Judge likewiſe and condemn <hi>your</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:43846:33"/> 
               <hi>ſelves,</hi> and your <hi>Sin</hi> as the meritorious cauſe of all your Sorrows and Sufferings. Never look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sin, but behold the <hi>long train</hi> of Evils that follow after it; and if you were not deliver'd from Sin it ſelf, this train of Evils would run <hi>Parallel</hi> with <hi>Eternity.</hi> God requires the <hi>Heart ſhould be humbled,</hi> and accept the <hi>Puniſhment of its Iniquity.</hi> The Heart muſt firmly believe that Sin is that, whereat God is diſpleaſed; that Sin is the procuring Cauſe of all other Evils that are felt, and that the true Reaſon of Gods Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, is <hi>becauſe, even becauſe</hi> his <hi>Word and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments</hi> have been caſt behind the back, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and broken,</hi> Levit. 26. 41, 43.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Under Affliction, be <hi>ſenſible of the Plagues of your own Hearts;</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> with <hi>Earneſt Deſire</hi> to have them <hi>preſently and throughly healed.</hi> The Sickneſs and Periſhing of the outward man, is for the <hi>reſtoring the inward man</hi> to Health. The Humours, and Appetites, and Inclinations of the Body, are an occaſion of much Sin in the Soul; which ſhould make you the more conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the <hi>Fleſh</hi> ſhould be <hi>diſeaſed,</hi> and <hi>pained,</hi> and <hi>ready to periſh,</hi> that the <hi>Spirit may be healed,</hi> and <hi>ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Corporal Diſeaſes, attain not their end, unleſs they make you ſenſible of <hi>Spiritual</hi> Maladies. Is thy Head, thy Breaſt, thy Back, or any part of thy Body out of Order? preſently look with a <hi>diligent ſearch</hi> into thy <hi>own Heart,</hi> to know what <hi>that ailes;</hi> that there may be the more ſerious and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43846:33"/> ſpeedy Application to the great Phyſician of Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ephraim</hi> when chaſtized was ſenſible of the <hi>ſtubbornneſs</hi> of corrupted Nature, and its <hi>back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs to come under the Yoak of God.</hi> I was ſays he, as a <hi>Bullock unaccuſtomed to the Yoak,</hi> and he prays not ſo much for the <hi>removal of the Rod,</hi> as for <hi>Grace</hi> that might <hi>Convert him</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> who did <hi>correct him.</hi> Afflictions are <hi>Spiritual Medicines</hi> much made uſe of by the Lord <hi>who heals his People.</hi> Sick-beds are the places where he <hi>Works great cures;</hi> when the <hi>Face is Pale,</hi> when the <hi>Pulſe beats diſorderly,</hi> when the <hi>Blood is boiling hot,</hi> and the whole Body in a <hi>Flame,</hi> and the frame of Nature ſeems juſt ready to be diſſolved; all this has a mighty Influence unto the <hi>Souls Healthineſs and Proſperity.</hi> How are <hi>dreggs</hi> then purged out, and how <hi>Pure, Humble,</hi> and <hi>Heavenly minded</hi> is the Heart then!</p>
            <p n="4">4. Under Affliction, <hi>deſire Inſtruction, and that you may learn all the Leſſons, which the Rod is ſent to teach you.</hi> You are commanded to <hi>hear</hi> the <hi>Rod,</hi> Mic. 6. 9. <hi>The Lords Voice cryeth unto the City, and the Man of Wiſdom ſhall ſee thy Name; hear ye the Rod and who hath appointed it.</hi> The Rod has a Voice, and 'tis ſtrong and ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; if you will but heed it, it will be very ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate and plain to you. Chaſtning is truly <hi>beatifical,</hi> makes the chaſtized bleſſed, when the Lord does chaſtize and teach together, or gives
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43846:34"/> 
               <hi>Inſtruction</hi> with and <hi>by</hi> Correction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. 12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man, whom thou chaſtneſt O Lord, and teacheſt him out of thy Law.</hi> When the Schoolmaſter has a Rod in his hand, has given ſeveral Laſhes, and is ready upon neglects and new faults to give more; how does the Scholar mind every Word his Maſter ſpeaks to him! with what Care and Diligence is his Leſſon learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Rod of God ſhould quicken Attention to his Voice, and cauſe a moſt ſerious regard to his whole Will and Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Is the Leſſon of the Rod concerning <hi>thy Pride?</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 5. <hi>Be cloathed with Humility, for God reſiſteth the Proud, but giveth Grace to the Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Is the Leſſon of the Rod concerning thy <hi>Love to the World?</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 15. <hi>Love not the World, neither the things that are in the World; if any man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him.</hi> Is the Leſſon of the Rod concerning <hi>thy Sloth?</hi> Heb. 6. 12. <hi>That ye be not ſlothful, but followers of them who through Faith and Patience inherit the Promiſes.</hi> Is the Leſſon of the Rod concerning thy <hi>fooliſh fleſhly and hurtful Luſts?</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 11. <hi>Dearly beloved, I beſeech you as Strangers and Pilgrims, abſtain from fleſhly Luſts which war againſt the Soul.</hi> Finally, Is the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Rod concerning thy <hi>unruly Paſſions?</hi> Prov. 14. 29. <hi>He that is ſlow to wrath is of great underſtanding, but he that is haſty of Spirit exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Folly.</hi> So that 'tis very viſible and expoſed to the view of all, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 20. <hi>The Wrath of</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:43846:34"/> 
               <hi>man worketh not the Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> Eph. 4. 31, 32. <hi>Let all bitterneſs and wrath, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking be put away from you with all malice; and be ye kind one to another, tender-hearted, forgiving one another; even as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven you.</hi> Whatever the Leſſon of the Rod be; let it be your care to be <hi>throughly</hi> inſtructed in it; and <hi>practiſe</hi> in thoſe who have <hi>learned to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Under Affliction, <hi>ſincerely turn and ſeek to that God who ſmites you.</hi> A thorough Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is the end of Correction. Take notice of the falſe ways in which you have gone aſtray, and how near you were to the brink of Eternal Perdition; venture not to take ſo much <hi>as one ſtep</hi> farther, in <hi>Hells Road.</hi> But return to God unfeignedly and with your <hi>whole Heart.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to be <hi>wholly His;</hi> that your <hi>whole man</hi> ſhould be at <hi>his Command,</hi> and have reſpect to <hi>all</hi> his Precepts without Exception, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 5, 6. <hi>Oh that my ways were directed to keep thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes! then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect unto all thy Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judah</hi> is branded for this, that they <hi>refuſed to turn</hi> to <hi>him</hi> that <hi>ſmote them.</hi> No wonder that Gods <hi>anger</hi> did <hi>abide,</hi> and that his hand was ſtill felt very heavy upon them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 12, 13. <hi>For all this his anger is not turned away; but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill; for this People turneth not to</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:43846:35"/> 
               <hi>him that ſmiteth them, neither do ſeek the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> The hand that ſmites you, if you will not turn, can give <hi>worſe blows;</hi> nay it can give a <hi>deadly blow,</hi> that may ſtrike you quite down, both into the <hi>Grave and Hell</hi> together. The hand that ſmites, <hi>alone can heal,</hi> therefore it concerns you to <hi>humble your ſelves</hi> under it.</p>
            <p>How great is the <hi>goodneſs of God,</hi> that <hi>he gives you leave</hi> to turn to him! that he <hi>requires you</hi> to ſeek him! and that for no leſs than his <hi>Favour,</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Glory,</hi> and <hi>Bleſſedneſs!</hi> And all this ſhall be yours, if you <hi>ſeek diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Under Affliction, take heed <hi>of deſpiſing the chaſtning of the Lord.</hi> Heb. 12. 5. <hi>Ye have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the Exhortation, that ſpeaketh unto you as unto Children, My Son deſpiſe not thou the chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Lord.</hi> Chaſtning is deſpiſed, when the Lords <hi>hand</hi> in chaſtning is not taken notice of, nor his <hi>end</hi> in Correcting is Minded or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with; when neither his <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in <hi>rebukes</hi> is obſerved; nor <hi>Sin mourned for,</hi> which does diſpleaſe him. Thus for a while chaſtning was deſpiſed by him, you read of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 17. <hi>For the Iniquity of his Covetouſneſs was I wroth and ſmote him, I hid me and was wroth, and he went frowardly on in the way of his Heart.</hi> But at laſt he was brought to a better temper. The Lord humbled him, and healed the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs of his Heart; and likewiſe removed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43846:35"/> his ſtroke from him, <hi>V.</hi> 18. <hi>I have ſeen his ways and will heal him, I will lead him alſo, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Comfort to him and to his Mourners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Affliction take notice of God as the <hi>Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter,</hi> elſe you <hi>contemn</hi> him; take notice of <hi>Sin,</hi> as the cauſe <hi>why</hi> you are afflicted; for if <hi>Sin</hi> be not <hi>laid to Heart,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> whom <hi>you Sin againſt</hi> is diſregarded. Nay Saints in a ſenſe deſpiſe chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, if they <hi>don't behold</hi> that the <hi>Rod</hi> they feel is in their <hi>Fathers hand,</hi> (for the Exhortation, the Apoſtle tells us, ſpeaks <hi>as unto Children,)</hi> and that it is a token of his Paternal Faithfulneſs and Love, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>Whom the Lord loveth he correcteth, even as a Father the Son in whom he delighteth.</hi> To look upon Afflictions meerly as evils is to deſpiſe them. They ought to be lookt upon as Arguments of Gods Fatherly Wiſdom and Care; and as <hi>Talents improvable</hi> to great Spiritual Advantage. The <hi>Cup</hi> is in the hand of a <hi>Father,</hi> and all the <hi>Ingredients</hi> in it are <hi>healing.</hi> Every <hi>Member of Chriſt,</hi> therefore ſhould ſpeak that <hi>Language,</hi> which his <hi>Head</hi> ſpake before him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18. 11. <hi>The Cup which my Father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, ſhall</hi> I <hi>not drink it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Under Affliction, <hi>faint not, neither be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Correction.</hi> He is infinitely <hi>wiſe</hi> who does correct, and therefore Correction ſhall not be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive</hi> but in <hi>meaſure,</hi> Jer. 30. 11. I <hi>am with thee, ſaith the Lord to ſave thee,</hi> I <hi>will not make a full end of thee, but will correct thee in meaſure</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:43846:36"/> 
               <hi>and not leave thee wholly unpuniſhed.</hi> The <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of Affliction is <hi>ſuch</hi> as he, who is <hi>beſt able to judge,</hi> ſees to be <hi>needful,</hi> and no more; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Now for a ſeaſon if need be, ye are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs through many Temptations.</hi> God will ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten your burthen; or if he ſhould <hi>add</hi> to your Load, he will <hi>proportion Strength,</hi> that you may be able to bear it. Faint not under his hand, for when he <hi>ſtrikes</hi> he alſo <hi>ſuſtains,</hi> and in <hi>Wrath remembers Mercy.</hi> Be willing that Affliction ſhould remain, till 'tis ſanctified, and has done its work for which 'twas laid upon you. 'Tis ſad, when Affliction goes off without doing any good to the afflicted; when the Rod is like the <hi>firſt King</hi> that <hi>Iſrael</hi> had, <hi>given in Gods Anger, and taken away in his Wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Lord afflicts; his Diſpenſations are <hi>mixed</hi> Checker-work; Black and White; <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Severity</hi> together; and there ſhould be a <hi>Mixture</hi> of <hi>Holy Affections</hi> that are <hi>diverſe</hi> one from the other, anſwerably in your Hearts. This is notably repreſented by <hi>one</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Poets,</hi> and his Verſes have a great deal of Senſe and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in them.</p>
            <l>Ah my dear angry Lord,</l>
            <l>Since thou doſt Love yet ſtrike; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herberts</hi> Bitter-ſweet. <hi>P.</hi> 165.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Caſt down yet help afford;</l>
            <l>Sure I will do the like.</l>
            <l>I will complain the Praiſe;</l>
            <l>I will bewail, approve:</l>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:43846:36"/>
            <l> And all my four-ſweet days,</l>
            <l>I will lament and love.</l>
            <p>Be not too eager for the removal of the ſtroke you ſmart under; that removal is but a <hi>common</hi> Mercy; but the <hi>Sanctification</hi> of it, is <hi>peculiar kindneſs,</hi> that which <hi>accompanies Salvation.</hi> If the Plaiſter lies not on long enough, it heals not the Sore; if the Potion be caſt up again, aſſoon as taken down, it works not a cure. <hi>God knows</hi> when <hi>'tis fitteſt</hi> to <hi>remove</hi> your trouble; therefore be <hi>dump with Silence</hi> and wait with Patience till <hi>this fitteſt time</hi> comes. <hi>David</hi> did ſo, though he was in an <hi>horrible Pit</hi> in the <hi>Miry Clay,</hi> he was not over eager to be pluckt out, but exerciſed Patience, and how Happy was the iſſue! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 1, 2, 3. <hi>I waited patiently for the Lord, and he inclined unto me and heard my cry; he brought me up alſo out of an horrible Pit, out of the Miry Clay, and ſet my Feet upon a Rock and eſtabliſhed my goings. And he hath put a new Song in my Mouth, even Praiſe unto our God; many ſhall ſee it and fear and truſt in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Under Affliction, let there be <hi>a moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Subjection to the Father of Spirits, Lights and Mercies.</hi> The Father of Spirits, will take <hi>ſpecial care</hi> of <hi>Souls;</hi> and conſult <hi>their Health</hi> and <hi>Reace,</hi> and <hi>endleſs welfare.</hi> If the Soul be ſafe, the <hi>Body muſt</hi> be <hi>ſafe</hi> in the <hi>ſame Bottom.</hi> The <hi>Body</hi> that belongs to a <hi>ſanctified Soul,</hi> muſt be a <hi>Glorious Body</hi> at the <hi>Reſurrection of the Juſt.</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:43846:37"/> And ſince the Lord is the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> you may conclude he <hi>perfectly underſtands,</hi> what is moſt <hi>conducive to your Intereſt,</hi> and what <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>degree</hi> of Affliction, is moſt expedient and <hi>beſt</hi> for you; and becauſe he is the <hi>Father of Mercies;</hi> Mercy he <hi>delights</hi> in, as a <hi>man</hi> does in his <hi>own off-ſpring;</hi> he will deal <hi>tenderly</hi> with you, Mercy ſhall not be <hi>forgotten</hi> in the <hi>greateſt Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Pſal.</hi> 103. 13. <hi>Like as a Father pittieth his Children, ſo the Lord pittieth them that fear him; for he knoweth our frame and remembreth we aye duſt.</hi> Subjection to God when he afflicts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes you, and beſides this Subjection is the <hi>way of Life.</hi> Heb. 12. 9. <hi>Furthermore we have had Fathers of our Fleſh, who corrected us, and we gave them Reverence; ſhall we not much rather be in Subjection to the Father of Spirits and live?</hi> Subjection to God is the wiſeſt courſe to have <hi>temporal Life prolonged,</hi> and liv'd <hi>to purpoſe,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> at length vouchſafed.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>ſecond Place,</hi> I am to direct you how to carry it <hi>after Affliction;</hi> now is a time of great danger, when the Heart is apt to ſhew both its <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Deceitfulneſs</hi> together, and to grow <hi>ſecure</hi> as if all <hi>Peril were over;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>1. Keep <hi>alive in your Hearts, the ſame Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of things</hi> after <hi>Affliction which you had</hi> under <hi>Affliction.</hi> Things <hi>are</hi> really as they <hi>were,</hi> though we of Sick grow well again, therefore our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43846:37"/> thoughts of them ſhould not alter. The great Truths revealed, and ſo much inſiſted on in the Word of God; in Affliction had deep Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon our Spirits. How <hi>clearly</hi> and <hi>concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly,</hi> did we then perceive, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saviour!</hi> that <hi>all things</hi> were juſtly to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>loſs</hi> that he might be <hi>gained!</hi> We lookt upon <hi>time</hi> as too <hi>precious</hi> a thing to be ſpent <hi>Idly</hi> or <hi>Wickedly.</hi> The Soul was lookt upon as <hi>more worth</hi> than the <hi>whole World,</hi> and more to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded;</hi> not to be neglected for the Worlds ſake, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 26. <hi>What ſhall it profit a man, if he ſhall gain the whole World and loſe his own Soul? or what ſhall a man give in exchange for his Soul?</hi> How did the thoughts of <hi>Eternity</hi> affect our Hearts, when we were in the depth of Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! Our Apprehenſions of this Truth were ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing. That all muſt quickly be <hi>in</hi> Eternity, and all muſt be <hi>unto</hi> Eternity, either in <hi>Joy</hi> or <hi>Wo.</hi> Our Conceptions of theſe and ſuch like things, were moſt <hi>rectified</hi> in Affliction; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when Affliction is removed, our Judgments ſhould ſtill remain the ſame. The concerns of <hi>another World</hi> ſhould always be eſteemed far greater, than the higheſt concerns of <hi>this.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs well becomes us, in thoſe matters which are of <hi>Everlaſting Conſequence,</hi> where careleſneſs or miſtake will iſſue in <hi>endleſs</hi> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine; <hi>underſtanding Diligence</hi> in <hi>Eternal</hi> Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>2. After Affliction, <hi>be very Jealous over</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:43846:38"/> 
               <hi>your own Spirits, which are ſo very prone to deal treacherouſly both with God and your ſelves.</hi> You are not naturally <hi>truſty to either;</hi> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful to God, and unfaithful to your own Souls. Hearken how the Lord complains, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6. 7. <hi>They like men have tranſgreſſed the Covenant, they have dealt treacherouſly againſt me.</hi> You do not know your <hi>ſelves to be men,</hi> if you don't know your ſelves to <hi>be treacherous;</hi> and ſtrongly inclined to <hi>break</hi> through all <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations</hi> in Point of <hi>Duty, Gratitude,</hi> and <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt it ſelf;</hi> which you are under: ever ſince the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> Apoſtacy and fall from God, his Poſterity have a vehement Propenſion <hi>to ſtart aſide alike deceitful bowes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A notable inſtance of the Hearts treachery in Afflictions, and inſtability upon the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of it, you have, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 34, 35, 36, 37. <hi>When he ſlew them then they ſought him, they returned and inquired early after God, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that God was their Rock, and the high God their Redeemer; nevertheleſs they did flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him with their Lips, and lied unto him with their Tongues, for their Heart was not right with him, neither were they ſtedfaſt in his Covenant.</hi> Mens <hi>Reſolutions</hi> in Afflictions, are like <hi>Nautarum Vota,</hi> the <hi>Vows of Marriners</hi> in a Storm, the <hi>firſt things</hi> that are <hi>broken</hi> when once they get <hi>ſafe to Shore.</hi> Be ſure therefore to <hi>check</hi> your hearts and lift them up to God to ſecure them, when <hi>firſt</hi> you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:43846:38"/> them ſo <hi>much as begin</hi> to <hi>ſtart aſide.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy <hi>begins</hi> in the <hi>Heart,</hi> that does firſt <hi>turn back from God,</hi> then afterwards <hi>the ſteps de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from his ways;</hi> diſtruſting therefore your own Hearts follow <hi>Solomons</hi> Counſel, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 23. <hi>And keep them with all diligence,</hi> and unto your own ſtricteſt Vigilancy, add fervent Prayer, that the Lord would make your Hearts <hi>clean Hearts,</hi> and that he would <hi>renew</hi> and keep your <hi>Spirits right</hi> with him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 10.</p>
            <p>3. Cry for <hi>Strength to be vouchſafed conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually from above, to perform your Reſolutions made in the day of your Affliction and Diſtreſs.</hi> If you are not <hi>ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his might,</hi> you will be too <hi>weak to do,</hi> what your ſelves with the <hi>greateſt firmneſs</hi> have ſeem'd to <hi>purpoſe.</hi> And you muſt pray hard, and 'tis worth praying for, that this <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> may reſt upon you. The Pſalmiſt ſaw his need of Strength from Heaven, he begg'd for it, and had it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138. 3. <hi>In the day, when I cried thou anſweredſt me, and ſtrengthnedſt me with ſtrength in my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are <hi>two</hi> ſorts of Reſolutions which are <hi>moſt commonly made,</hi> but neither of them are kept; ſo as the <hi>Reſolvers</hi> thought they would be. Reſolutions meerly to <hi>ſtop</hi> and <hi>gag</hi> the Mouth of a <hi>clamorous Conſcience;</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions which are made in <hi>mens own ſtrength,</hi> who <hi>Queſtion</hi> not, <hi>nor trouble their Heads</hi> much
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43846:39"/> about, their <hi>Ability</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> to perform them. Theſe Reſolutions ſhews their falſhood, and fickleneſs; and how <hi>bold men</hi> are to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble</hi> with God; and how fooliſh in <hi>truſting</hi> and <hi>cheating</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Religious Purpoſes</hi> of the Pſalmiſt were of another Nature, in another manner. He is indeed very ſerious and <hi>Peremptory</hi> in his Reſolution, and confirmed it with <hi>a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſory Oath; Pſal.</hi> 119. 106. <hi>I have ſworn and I will perform it, that I will keep thy Righteous Judgments.</hi> But he is ſenſible, that neither his own Power, Promiſe, nor Oath were <hi>ſtrong enough to hold him;</hi> and keep him ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt to theſe Teſtimonies of God, therefore he prays <hi>twice together</hi> to be <hi>upheld, Pſal.</hi> 119. 16, 17. <hi>Uphold me according to thy Word that I may live, and let me not be aſhamed of my Hope.</hi> And again, <hi>Hold thou me up, and I ſhall be ſafe, ſo ſhall I have reſpect to thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes continually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After Affliction, <hi>take heed of that which your Hearts naturally are moſt prone to Idolize.</hi> Whatever has had <hi>Gods Room,</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>higheſt Room</hi> in your Hearts; is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your <hi>Idol.</hi> Be very ſtrict in the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to find the Idol out, and be ſure to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it; let it be at the <hi>Footſtool,</hi> while the Lord alone in the <hi>Throne,</hi> and has by far the Preeminence above it in your Affections. If
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43846:39"/> any of you <hi>Love Pleaſure more than God,</hi> Pleaſure is your <hi>Idol,</hi> or if you love Gain more than God, or if you love Relations, Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Ornaments more than God; theſe things are Idolized; now remember how <hi>vain</hi> the <hi>Idol</hi> was in your Affliction and Diſtreſs, and how <hi>helpleſs</hi> then it was found. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of Senſe, the earthly Treaſures, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; and other things you were ſo fond of, you were <hi>forced</hi> to ſee that <hi>help was not in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Heathen Poet notably expreſſes this.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Non domus, &amp; fundus; non aeris acervus &amp; auri;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Aegroto domini deduxit corpore febres;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Non animo curas—</hi>Horat. <hi>Epiſt</hi> 2. l. 1.</l>
            <p>Which may be thus Engliſhed.</p>
            <l>Nor Houſe, nor Lands, nor heaps of golden Ore;</l>
            <l>Can feaveriſh owners unto Health reſtore;</l>
            <l>Nor eaſe their Minds of Care.—</l>
            <p>Idolatry in a ſpecial manner provokes the Lord to Jealouſie; The <hi>bowing</hi> of the <hi>Knee</hi> to <hi>Images,</hi> as Pagans and Papiſts do; <hi>diſpleaſes</hi> the <hi>Onely true God.</hi> But if that <hi>leading</hi> affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Love,</hi> which is one of the <hi>higheſt pieces</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> is placed principally upon any thing beſides God; hereby his anger and jealouſie is blown up to a great heat and hight; and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43846:40"/> mark, what the Apoſtle ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 22. <hi>Do we provoke the Lord to Jealouſie? are we ſtronger than he?</hi> As his <hi>Strength</hi> is <hi>infinitely beyond</hi> ours; ſo there is an <hi>Infiniteneſs</hi> in the <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Madneſs,</hi> when any Adventure to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him to Jealouſie. Love is the greateſt Grace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 13. Love is the <hi>firſt and great Commandment;</hi> what ever therefore is moſt apt to ſteal away your Love from God, keep your <hi>Hearts, while you live, ſhut</hi> againſt it with an <hi>Holy Indignation,</hi> Hoſ. 14. 8. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim ſhall ſay, what have I to do any more with Idols? I have heard him and obſerved him: I am like a green Fir-tree, from me is thy Fruit found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. After Affliction, be <hi>diligent againſt the Sin, which does moſt eaſily beſet you,</hi> Heb. 12. 1. <hi>Let us lay aſide every weight, and the Sin which does ſo eaſily beſet us, and let us run with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the race which is ſet before us.</hi> Every Sin is a <hi>Weight and Clog.</hi> I wiſh that every one lookt upon it as ſuch! But the Sin, which by Reaſon of our <hi>Complexions, Callings,</hi> or the <hi>general Practice</hi> in the Age and Place we live in; is moſt <hi>apt to Prevail;</hi> that is the <hi>heavy Weight,</hi> and the <hi>worſt Clog</hi> of all to hinder us in our running the Chriſtian Race.</p>
            <p>You had need to be watchful againſt the Corruption of your Nature which though there
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43846:40"/> be the Grace of God in Truth in you, is far from being perfectly healed; and is ready upon all Occaſions, and Temptations, to break forth, to the diſpleaſing of God, the wounding of your Conſciences, the defiling of your Souls, and the diſturbance of your Peace.</p>
            <p>And <hi>whatſoever Iniquity</hi> it is, which becauſe it pretends your <hi>Security</hi> from danger, or your <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Gain;</hi> you find your ſelves <hi>moſt ſtrongly addicted to;</hi> verily there is need of the ſtricter watch, and more fervent Prayer; that you may not be <hi>overcome</hi> by, nay that you may not ſo much as <hi>enter into Temptation.</hi> The Sin which does moſt eaſily beſet you, has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done you the greateſt miſchief, and is likely to do you more ſtill; and if you ſhould at laſt <hi>fall into Hell; This</hi> would be one of the <hi>heavieſt weights</hi> to <hi>ſink you thither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. After Affliction <hi>beware of ſloath and Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Live the <hi>reſt of your time in the Fleſh, not to the Luſts of men; but to the Will of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 2. Let not <hi>your own Luſts,</hi> as ſo many <hi>Cormorants devour</hi> your time, while you are making Proviſion for them, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling them. And let not the Luſts, Humours and Pleaſures of <hi>others</hi> have <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>time</hi> at <hi>Command.</hi> And though they <hi>think it ſtrange, that you run not with them to the ſame exceſs of Riot, ſpeaking evil of you,</hi> yet be not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged; for <hi>they ſhall give an account unto him</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:43846:41"/> 
               <hi>that is ready to Judge the quick and the dead,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 4, 5. And that Judge will <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them,</hi> and will <hi>Approve and Reward</hi> your <hi>Diligence</hi> in <hi>ſeeking</hi> him, and <hi>working</hi> for him.</p>
            <p>You have <hi>not improved</hi> your Afflictions, if you have not <hi>ceaſed to waſt,</hi> if you have not <hi>learned</hi> to improve your <hi>time.</hi> In your Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Diſtreſs, what a <hi>view had you of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity?</hi> and what a trouble was it to you, that ſuch a deal of time had been ſtolen away and loſt in Sin and Vanity? Perhaps Eternity was ſo amazing, in the <hi>vaſtneſs</hi> and <hi>unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs</hi> of it; that you concluded, that if you were to live <hi>Methuſelahs</hi> Age; 'twould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to miſpend wilfully <hi>one hour</hi> of it. Now after Affliction is over; and ſo little of your time is behind; will you be <hi>laviſh</hi> of that time <hi>ſtill:</hi> will you <hi>loſe</hi> any <hi>more?</hi> Oh ſee the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of <hi>redeeming</hi> Time, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 15, 16. <hi>See then that ye walk circumſpectly not as Fools but as wiſe, redeeming the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the days are evil.</hi> And <hi>fear</hi> the <hi>loſs</hi> of time, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>If ye call on the Father, who without reſpect of Perſons judgeth according to every mans work; paſs the time of your ſojourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here in fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be ſure to loſe no more; for to loſe <hi>all your time;</hi> is moſt certainly to <hi>loſe your ſelves,</hi> and that <hi>for ever.</hi> In the other World there
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43846:41"/> is <hi>no obtaining</hi> Mercy by thoſe who all the while they were in this World, <hi>ſlighted</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. There is no <hi>working</hi> out your <hi>own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> after death; if all your Life-time Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation be neglected.</p>
            <p>7. After Affliction <hi>be full of gratitude, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ingenuity and Love.</hi> The <hi>Calves of your Lips,</hi> moſt acceptable Sacrifices; ſhould be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red frequently, nay continually, with an <hi>enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> Heart, with a <hi>willing</hi> mind. <hi>David</hi> was in danger of loſing his Life among the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines,</hi> God preſerves it. How <hi>Fruitful</hi> are his <hi>Lips</hi> in Praiſes! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>I will bleſs the Lord at all times, his Praiſe ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually be in my Mouth; my Soul ſhall make her boaſt in the Lord; the humble ſhall hear thereof and be glad. Oh magnifie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his Name together! I ſought the Lord, and he heard me, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me from all my fears.</hi> Hezekiah had been deliver'd from <hi>deadly</hi> Sickneſs, he was raiſed by ſpecial Favour and Power; when according to Nature, Death was unavoidable. Coming ſo unexpectedly and ſo quickly from a <hi>ſeeming Death-Bed</hi> to the <hi>Temple,</hi> how does he make that <hi>Temple Ring</hi> with his Thanskgivings! <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38. 17, 19. <hi>Behold for Peace, I had great bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs; but thou haſt in love to my Soul deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd it from the Pit of Corruption; thou haſt caſt all my Sins behind thy back. The li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, the living, he ſhall Praiſe thee as I do</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:43846:42"/> 
               <hi>this day: the Father to the Children ſhall make known thy Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not onely muſt your Mouths be fill'd with Praiſes, but your <hi>Hearts with Love;</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity ſhould make you ſtudy what to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto God. Obſerve the <hi>working</hi> of the Pſalmiſts <hi>grateful Breaſt,</hi> after God had <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd his Soul from Death, his Eyes from Tears and his Feet from falling,</hi> Pſal. 116. 1. <hi>I love the Lord becauſe he hath heard my Voice and my Supplication.</hi> V. 3. <hi>The Sorrows of Death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me, the Pains of Hell got hold upon me.</hi> V. 5, 6. <hi>Gracious is the Lord and Righteous, yea our God is merciful; I was brought low and he helped me.</hi> V. 7. <hi>Return to thy reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee.</hi> V. 12. <hi>What ſhall I render to the Lord for all his Benefits towards me?</hi> He thought nothing <hi>too good,</hi> nothing <hi>too much</hi> for that God, who had been <hi>ſo good</hi> to him; who had done <hi>ſo much</hi> for him!</p>
            <p>Still you ſhould be <hi>contriving</hi> to make more <hi>ſuitable</hi> returns for what you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and with your Praiſes and Service, your <hi>Hearts and Love</hi> muſt be the <hi>Principal part</hi> of the returns you make. Love lies in <hi>Deſire</hi> and <hi>Delight;</hi> no <hi>Mercies</hi> ſo <hi>deſirable</hi> as the <hi>Father of Mercies;</hi> God <hi>Himſelf</hi> is more to be <hi>delighted in</hi> than any of the <hi>Benefits</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows. Take heed of loving <hi>Deliverance</hi> more
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:43846:42"/> than your <hi>Deliverer.</hi> Mercies themſelves are <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolized,</hi> and it provokes the Lord to <hi>Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie;</hi> if <hi>they</hi> are <hi>prized</hi> and <hi>delighted</hi> in, more than the <hi>Lord God of your Mercies.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pſalmiſt, though he valued Deliverance from Enemies, and Trouble; yet principally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joices in God himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 2. <hi>I will be glad and rejoice in Thee, I will Praiſe thy Name O thou moſt High!</hi> Rejoice in God more than in the return of Health, more than in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longation of Life, or any other Comfort and Enjoyment. Mercies attain their end, when God is more endeared to you by them. God will be <hi>all in all</hi> in <hi>Heaven;</hi> and the more he is <hi>your all</hi> at preſent, the <hi>more of Heaven</hi> you enjoy on <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8. After Affliction be <hi>ſenſible you are not ſafe in your own Hands; therefore commit the keeping of your Souls to God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 19. <hi>Let them commit the keeping of their Souls to Him in well-doing, as unto a Faithful Creator.</hi> If you are indeed wiſe and <hi>know</hi> your ſelves, you will <hi>diſtruſt</hi> your ſelves. <hi>Self-Confidence</hi> is an undeniable Argument of <hi>Self-Ignorance.</hi> Truſt your ſelves in no hands, but thoſe out of which <hi>none</hi> ſhall ever be able to <hi>pluck you,</hi> and thoſe are hands of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Father, Joh.</hi> 10. 27, 28, 29. <hi>My Sheep hear my Voice, and I know them and they follow me, and I give unto them Life Eternal, and they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver periſh, neither ſhall any pluck them out of</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:43846:43"/> 
               <hi>my hand; My Father which gave them me is greater than All, and none is able to pluck them out of my Fathers hand.</hi> Not onely in the Hour and Agony of Death; but all your <hi>lives long;</hi> every <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Hour,</hi> you have need ſtill to be <hi>commending your Spirits unto God:</hi> for they are ſafe with none beſides, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. 5. <hi>Into thy hands do I commit my Spirit, thou haſt redeemed me, O Lord God of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE IV. Of Counſel more <hi>peculiarly</hi> to <hi>Saints,</hi> who are <hi>afflicted.</hi> Shew your ſelves to be Saints indeed, and let your Graces now be much in Exerciſe. <hi>Spices beaten</hi> in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, are the more <hi>Fragrant;</hi> Afflicted Saints ſhould manifeſt a <hi>rare and excellent Spirit;</hi> but no <hi>Diſſatisfaction</hi> or <hi>Diſcontent;</hi> conſidering the Truth of this Doctrine, <hi>that they are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted for their good.</hi> You that are Saints; in your Troubles you <hi>need</hi> Counſel; and 'tis not to be doubted but you will <hi>heed</hi> it; I ſhall give it in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be <hi>Patient whatever your Affliction is.</hi> That <hi>God</hi> whom you ſerve is patient to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Man;</hi> has been patient towards <hi>you;</hi> how many affronts and Provocations has he born, put up, and pardoned! The Lord Jeſus Chriſt was a <hi>Pattern</hi> of <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs;</hi> When he was <hi>reviled of Men, he reviled not again; when he ſuffered he threatned not,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 23. Nay many had <hi>Life by his Blood,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:43846:43"/> who <hi>imbrued</hi> their hands in <hi>that Blood</hi> and <hi>ſhed</hi> it. And when it <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vivificat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſti ſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guine, etiam qui fudit ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti; Talis eſt Chriſti ac tanta patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia; quae niſi talis exiſteret; Paulum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Apoſtolum Eccleſia non haberet.</hi> Cypr. <hi>de bono Patientiae.</hi> p. <hi>mihi</hi> 316.</note> pleaſed his <hi>Father to bruiſe him and to put him to grief, yet as a Lamb brought to the ſlaughter; and as a Sheep before her Shearers is dumb; ſo he opened not his Mouth.</hi> Iſa. 53. 7. The Members of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhould imitate Chriſt the Head in Patience.</p>
            <p>It may be an Inducement to a quiet bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Affliction; that <hi>far worſe</hi> has been <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merited</hi> by the <hi>very beſt,</hi> than is <hi>endured,</hi> Ezr. 9. 13. <hi>Thou our God haſt puniſhed us leſs than our Iniquities deſerve.</hi> But the <hi>Benefit</hi> of Affliction, proves that Patience is a <hi>Grace</hi> with a <hi>great deal of Reaſon</hi> in it; for who can ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally take it ill, when good comes to them; and <hi>ſpiritual kindneſſes,</hi> which are the moſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> kindneſſes, are <hi>done</hi> them?</p>
            <p>I have demonſtrated the good of Affliction to the Saints; I ſhall now demonſtrate, the <hi>good of Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Patience is your great <hi>Security,</hi> and makes you to <hi>keep Poſſeſſion of your Selves,</hi> Luk. 21. 19. <hi>In your Patience, poſſeſs ye your Souls.</hi> A Patient man, whatever he loſes, whatever he ſuffers, is <hi>ſtill himſelf,</hi> not diſcompoſed, not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43846:44"/> diſtracted and <hi>hurried away</hi> from the <hi>Conduct</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of that <hi>Holy Wiſdom,</hi> and the <hi>Grace of God</hi> which is in Him. By <hi>Patient Continuance</hi> in well-doing, and by patient <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi> rather than he will <hi>ceaſe</hi> in well-doing, his Soul is ſafe, and ſhall never be loſt; <hi>for he that endures to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Mat. 24. 13. And in what a <hi>calm</hi> has he Poſſeſſion of his own Spirit, when his <hi>outward Condition</hi> is moſt <hi>Stormy</hi> and <hi>Tempeſtuous!</hi> He has <hi>caſt Anchor within the Vail;</hi> and that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor is <hi>ſure and ſtedfaſt,</hi> Heb. 6. 19. Keeps his Mind from Fluctuation and toſſing too and fro. Patience is the Souls <hi>Garriſon,</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves</hi> it in that <hi>Peace;</hi> which neither <hi>Earth</hi> nor <hi>Hell</hi> are able to <hi>diſturb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Patience is that which <hi>makes you perfect,</hi> Jam. 1. 4. <hi>But let Patience have its perfect work, that ye may be perfect and entire wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nothing.</hi> The more there is of Chriſtian Patience, and Strength to perſevere both in Active and Paſſive Obedience, which God calls you to; 'tis an Argument you are arrived to the greater Degree of Perfection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Grace and Holineſs. And beſides this, Patience will make you <hi>leſs concerned</hi> at thoſe <hi>Wants;</hi> which to <hi>impatient</hi> Creatures are <hi>ſo ſenſible an Affliction.</hi> He that is very Patient under <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> may truly be ſaid not ſo much to <hi>want health;</hi> He that is Patient under Poverty, does not ſo much want Riches. The Chriſtian is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:43846:44"/> at the want of thoſe things, which he can be contentedly without. Patience made the Apoſtle go through great variety of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions with a moſt even and compoſed Mind and Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 4, 8, 9, 10. <hi>In all things approving our ſelves as the Miniſters of God in much Patience, in Affliction, in Neceſſities, in Diſtreſſes; By Honour and Diſhonour, by evil Report and good Report, as deceivers and yet true; as unknown, and yet well known; as dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and behold we live; as chaſtned, and not kill'd; as ſorrowful, yet always rejoycing; as Poor, yet making many Rich; as having nothing and yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Patience very well <hi>becomes you,</hi> conſidering the <hi>Relation</hi> you ſtand in to God, who is a Father <hi>too Good and Wiſe,</hi> to give to any of his Children, a <hi>juſt ground</hi> for <hi>unſubmiſſion,</hi> things cannot be ordered better or with more Wiſdom than He orders them. The <hi>compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of your <hi>Wills</hi> with <hi>His;</hi> will be a great evidence that you are <hi>renewed in the Spirit of your Minds,</hi> and that you have the <hi>new Heart</hi> promiſed in the new Covenant. And this Patience of yours being <hi>manifeſted</hi> in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you feel from the <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man;</hi> will be a great <hi>Credit to Religion;</hi> and a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction to the World,</hi> that there is a <hi>great Efficacy</hi> in the <hi>Truth</hi> of the Goſpel, and in the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> which can carry you ſo <hi>far beyond the Strength of Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:43846:45"/>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Patientia eſt quae nos Deo commendat &amp; ſervat. Ipſa eſt quae iram temperat; quae linguam fraenat, quae mentem gubernat, pacem cuſtodit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendium ſimultatis extinguit, coercet potentiam divitum, inopiam pauperum refovet; facit humiles in proſperis, in adverſis fortes; contra inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias &amp; contumelias mites; tentationes expugnat, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutiones tolerat, paſſiones &amp; martyria conſummat.</hi> Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. <hi>De Patientiae bono,</hi> pag. <hi>mihi</hi> 319.</note> Finally Patience will make and keep you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, it will reſtrain Anger, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other diſturbing Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it will bridle the Tongue; keep the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit under Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, it will extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh Contention, and keep Peace from being broken. It will be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive of the Power of the Rich; and it will refreſh the needineſs of the Poor. It will make you humble in the height of Proſperity; ſo ſtrong as not to faint in the depth of Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; it will make you mild againſt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt injuries, it will break the force of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and fortifie you againſt Perſecution; though it ſhould riſe ſo high as Martyrdom. Let all this perſwade you to the exerciſe of this admirable Grace of Patience; and ſee that it fail not in Affliction. Cry to the Lord for the increaſe of it, and that nothing may be too hard or heavy for it. He is called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The God of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Conſolation;</hi> the more Patience is wrought in you; you are likely to Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the greater Comfort.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:43846:45"/> 2. You that are afflicted Saints, <hi>Pray that your Faith may be ſo far from failing, that it may continually be increaſing.</hi> Faith is a Grace of great Neceſſity and Uſe; the Chriſtian <hi>lives</hi> by Faith; he <hi>ſees</hi> by Faith; he <hi>ſtands</hi> by Faith; he <hi>works</hi> by Faith; and is <hi>kept</hi> through Faith unto Salvation. In Affliction Faith is the Saints mighty ſupport; for Faith <hi>bears hard</hi> upon the <hi>Faithfulneſs of God,</hi> which will never fail; God is faithful not onely in giving the <hi>good things</hi> he has promiſed; but alſo in <hi>vouchſafing Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> which he ſees 'tis <hi>needful.</hi> The Pſalmiſt ſpeaks thus. <hi>I have believed, therefore have I ſpoken, I was greatly afflicted,</hi> Pſal. 116. 10. The <hi>greatneſs</hi> of Affliction <hi>hindred not</hi> the <hi>Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Faith;</hi> but his Faith hindred <hi>his fainting</hi> under the greateſt Affliction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 13. <hi>I had fainted, unleſs I had believed to ſee the goodneſs of the Lord in the Land of the living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God may be <hi>truſted</hi> in, though he <hi>hides</hi> his face; though there are <hi>rebukes and frowns</hi> in his Countenance; God may be truſted in, though his <hi>ways are Dark and Cloudy,</hi> and his <hi>Hand heavy.</hi> Nay Holy <hi>Job</hi> ſays, <hi>Though he ſlay me yet will I truſt in him,</hi> Job 13. 15. Though the Providence of God ſeems hardly reconcileable with his Promiſes; but looks as if it thwarted his Promiſes; this is onely <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptio viſus,</hi> the Eyes miſtake. Let <hi>Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:43846:46"/> what <hi>Senſe</hi> cannot <hi>diſcern,</hi> and <hi>Senſe</hi> will be <hi>forced</hi> at laſt to <hi>grant,</hi> that <hi>Faith</hi> was in the right.</p>
            <p>In all Afflictions God is making good his <hi>Everlaſting Covenant, which is well ordered in all things and ſure,</hi> he is ſtill purſuing his deſign of Mercy towards his People, and promoting the Work of Grace, and Salvation. <hi>Believe</hi> this and <hi>reſt ſatisfied,</hi> onely let deſires be ſtrong, that what God deſigns in ſending Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, may be attained; and that his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline may be to good effect and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You afflicted Saints, <hi>give Glory to God, who afflicts you.</hi> Here you muſt know that God is of none, but of himſelf; his Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons undenied; He is unchangeable, no Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can be made to his Eſſential Excellency or his Bleſſedneſs. As all that come to him find him <hi>All-ſufficient,</hi> ſo, which is a <hi>great deal more,</hi> He is <hi>Self-ſufficient;</hi> Infinitely <hi>more</hi> muſt be to the <hi>Bleſſedneſs of God,</hi> then would <hi>be enough,</hi> for the Bleſſedneſs of <hi>ten thouſand Worlds</hi> of <hi>Men and Angels.</hi> So that your glorifying of God is <hi>apprehending, acknowledging, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Glory,</hi> not <hi>making him really more glorious than he was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Glorifie God by Believing him to be what he has revealed himſelf, by giving him the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:43846:46"/> higheſt room in your Hearts; depend upon him for all things. This Fountain of living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is glorified, when Saints always lie at it, perpetually derive Streams from it, and the broken Ciſterns are forſaken. Glorifie God by an higher Valuation of his Favour in Chriſt; and a greater Contempt of earthly things in Compariſon. Glorifie God by more willing ſervice, and reſolute cleaving to him. God is honoured indeed, when nothing can ſeparate the Saints from him: When neither the fier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Wind (to allude to the Tabb) can blow away, nor the hotteſt Sun can make them to caſt away that <hi>change of Raiment</hi> with which he has <hi>cloathed</hi> them. When they can ſay with the Church of old, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. 17, 18, 19. <hi>All this is come upon us, yet have we not forgotten Thee, neither have we dealt falſly in thy Covenant; Our Heart is not turned back from thee, neither have our ſteps declined from thy ways; though thou haſt ſore broken us in the Place of Dragons, and covered us with the Shaddow of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, Glorifie God by <hi>ſuch Works,</hi> as are <hi>not a denial of God;</hi> but a Demonſtration, <hi>what a Lord</hi> he is; and what his <hi>Grace is able</hi> to <hi>effect.</hi> The <hi>Works</hi> of many <hi>Profeſſors</hi> prove them <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> Tit. 1. 16. <hi>They profeſs that they know God, but in Works deny him, being abominable and diſobedient, and to every good work reprobate.</hi> But when Saints by <hi>good</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:43846:47"/> 
               <hi>Works</hi> are <hi>ſhining Lights;</hi> hereby Glory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to their Heavenly Father. For as the Works of Creation, are an Argument to prove moſt plainly <hi>an Eternal Power and Godhead;</hi> ſo the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>New Creatures,</hi> ſo <hi>different</hi> from, and ſo <hi>excellent</hi> above the Works of <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> make it evident that <hi>God is in</hi> theſe New Creatures; and his <hi>Grace is with</hi> them of a Truth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You afflicted Saints, <hi>obſerve the Special Sins, for which your Father is angry with you, and corrects you.</hi> That Grace which is in you makes you weary of its contrary; and the more Grace you have, the more weary you will be of Sin which remains in you. Cry to be <hi>cleanſed from faults</hi> that are ſo <hi>ſecret;</hi> that they hardly are <hi>diſcerned</hi> to be faults, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 12. <hi>Lurking Feavers,</hi> how dangerous are they! and much more dangerous are <hi>latent Corruptions.</hi> Therefore <hi>Surely it is meet to be ſaid unto God, I have born Chaſtiſement, I will not offend any more; that which I ſee not teach thou me, if I have done Iniquity I will do no more.</hi> Job 34. 31, 32. Find out, and <hi>purge out all the old Leaven,</hi> whether it be the Leaven of Pride, or Hypocriſie, or Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-mindedneſs, or Uncharitableneſs or any other <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> that ye may be <hi>a new Lump as ye are unleavened.</hi> The <hi>bitter Cup</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended as a <hi>purging Potion.</hi> Earneſtly therefore deſire, that the Iniquity which has moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:43846:47"/> and defiled you, may be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p n="5">5. You afflicted Saints <hi>anſwer the Lords Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations from you, leſt Wrath from the Lord be upon you.</hi> He is ſometimes very ſevere to them, that are very dear to him. He <hi>forgives their Iniquities, but takes Vengeance of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions,</hi> Pſal. 99. 8. That eminent <hi>Moſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing provoked in his Spirit ſpake unadviſedly with his Lips,</hi> Pſal. 106. 33. And that Word <hi>coſt him his Life.</hi> He falls, before <hi>Iſrael</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into <hi>Canaan. Hezekiah</hi> was a <hi>Gracious Man,</hi> full <hi>of Faith</hi> himſelf; and a <hi>Prince ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry zealous for the Reformation of</hi> Judah. See what a Character is given him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31. 20, 21. <hi>Thus did</hi> Hezekiah <hi>throughout all</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, <hi>and wrought that which was good and Right, and Truth before the Lord his God; And in every Work, that he began in the Service of the Houſe of God; and in the Law, and in the Commandments to ſeek his God, he did it with all his Heart and proſpered.</hi> And yet this Excellent King after Affliction, not watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Heart, but Suffering it to be <hi>lifted</hi> up; <hi>Wrath</hi> 'tis ſaid <hi>was upon him,</hi> 2 Chron. 32. 35.</p>
            <p>Though Gods Love to his Children be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver turned into <hi>hatred;</hi> yet notwithſtanding his Love to them, he may be <hi>very angry</hi> with them; he may take them up and laſh them
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:43846:48"/> in the view of all, to <hi>vindicate his Holineſs,</hi> and to make it evident, that he takes <hi>no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Wickedneſs</hi> by <hi>whomſoever</hi> it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. After you have felt his ſtrokes, <hi>fear</hi> your Fathers <hi>Frowns and Anger;</hi> pleaſe him in all things and <hi>abound</hi> in ſo doing; this he juſtly looks for, after he has ſhewn <hi>Care and Kindneſs</hi> both in <hi>Correcting</hi> you, and in <hi>fling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Rod</hi> out of his hand.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let the Rod, you have <hi>been chaſtized with, cauſe you to mend your Pace in Heavens way.</hi> Why ſhould Saints be as ſo many <hi>Snails,</hi> who ought rather to be <hi>ſwifter than Eagles</hi> haſting to the Prey? Is there ſuch an Holy and Mighty <hi>Spirit</hi> to <hi>help</hi> your Infirmities? Are there <hi>ſuch Promiſes</hi> of <hi>aſſiſting Grace?</hi> Is there ſuch a <hi>glorious Crown</hi> and <hi>Prize</hi> at the <hi>end of the race?</hi> And does your Salvation <hi>grow nearer</hi> and nearer every day? Oh put on with greater ſpeed. And let not a <hi>greater Violence</hi> be uſed by earthly men for meer <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles;</hi> than is by you, for the <hi>Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> Imitate thoſe wiſely eager ones, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 12. <hi>From the days of</hi> John <hi>the Baptiſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til now, the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and the Violent take it by force.</hi> Imitate the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who though he had labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo abundantly, was far from tiring, but preſs't on ſtill with greater forwardneſs <hi>towards the Mark, for the prize of the high Calling of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:43846:48"/> 7. Abound in <hi>that Work for God here upon Earth, which cannot be done when you come to Heaven.</hi> Fill up your Time, well with that buſineſs, which will ceaſe when you enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Eternity. The <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Goſpel may do <hi>much</hi> at <hi>preſent,</hi> which they <hi>cannot</hi> do <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> Now they may <hi>warn Sinners to flee from the Wrath to come.</hi> Now they may <hi>call them to turn from their evil ways and live;</hi> now they may <hi>pray them in Chriſts ſtead to be reconciled to God.</hi> Now they <hi>may take heed to all the Flock over which the Holy Ghoſt has made them overſeers to feed the Church of God, which he has purchaſed with his own Blood,</hi> Acts 20. 28. And take <hi>heed to their Miniſtry which they have received in the Lord, that they may fulfil it,</hi> Col. 4. 17. Now they may ſhew themſelves in <hi>all things Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of good Works,</hi> Examples to the Flock; always <hi>labouring fervently for them in Prayer, that they may ſtand perfect and compleat in all the Will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtians alſo have their Work <hi>now</hi> to do; which cannot be done in the other World. Now they may <hi>adorn the Doctrine of God their Saviour in all things.</hi> Now with <hi>well-doing they may put to ſilence the Ignorance of fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh men,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 15. Now by a Conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Performance of Relative Duties, they may be great Bleſſings to their Relations, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:43846:49"/> promote their Eternal Intereſt. They <hi>may be blameleſs and harmleſs without rebuke; in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Nation,</hi> acting <hi>like the Children of God, ſhining as Lights in the World, holding forth the Word of Life,</hi> Phil. 2. 14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p>But when once <hi>Death has ſeized</hi> on the Preachers of the Word, their <hi>Mouths are ſtopt with Earth,</hi> and they are <hi>effectually ſilenced;</hi> they can ſpeak unto, and overſee the Church no longer. At Death alſo Chriſtian's Work is at an end in this World; therefore before the approach of <hi>Deaths Night,</hi> when it will be too late to work; Let all in the mean time work the harder.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Though you <hi>are deliver'd out of Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, recover'd from your Diſtempers, be ſure to die daily.</hi> So did the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 31. Dying daily, implies a <hi>daily Meditation</hi> of Death, looking upon your ſelves every day within <hi>the reach of Death,</hi> and a continual <hi>preparedneſs for Death,</hi> and a ſtedfaſt <hi>Reſolution</hi> rather to <hi>ſuffer Death,</hi> than to make <hi>Shipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience.</hi> Do not rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon upon long Life; but be perſwaded, to live <hi>well</hi> is to live <hi>indeed.</hi> Live as thoſe that <hi>muſt</hi> die <hi>certainly;</hi> as thoſe that <hi>may</hi> die <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly.</hi> Be not offended at the <hi>Croſs</hi> of Chriſt, though it ſhould ly <hi>ſo heavy</hi> upon you, as to <hi>preſs you</hi> to Death. Sinful <hi>ſaving</hi> the Life,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:43846:49"/> is <hi>loſing it;</hi> but they who are valiant for the Truth of Chriſt, and will venture the <hi>loſing of Life for Chriſts ſake, ſhall find it,</hi> Mat. 16. 25. And if <hi>natural Life</hi> be continued; be earneſtly deſirous that <hi>Spiritual Life and livelineſs</hi> may be increaſed. Pray to be <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt often does, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. and look unto Jeſus, who is a quickning Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 45. <hi>The firſt Man</hi> Adam <hi>was made a living Soul, the laſt</hi> Adam <hi>was made a quickning Spirit.</hi> As he has given you Life, ſo he is ready to give it <hi>more and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly;</hi> this will make you to <hi>live to him,</hi> and to be unweariedly <hi>active for him.</hi> The quickned Apoſtl's earneſt deſire was that Chriſt might be magnified by him; his <hi>Life was at his Lords Service;</hi> and he was ready to <hi>die alſo to ſerve him.</hi> Phil. 1. 20. <hi>According to my ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Expectation and my Hope, that in nothing I ſhall be aſhamed, but that with all boldneſs, as always, ſo now alſo, Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my Body, whether it be by Life or by Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE V. Of <hi>Conſolation</hi> to Saints to whom it is <hi>ſo good,</hi> when they are <hi>afflicted.</hi> Unto the <hi>Righteous there ariſeth Light in the Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> The <hi>Rainbow,</hi> the <hi>emblem</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>token</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> is often <hi>ſeen</hi> in the <hi>blackeſt Cloud.</hi> The Saints are never in <hi>ſuch depths;</hi> but Comfort belongs to them, 'tis <hi>good</hi> for them to be <hi>as they are;</hi> nay all things conſidered; 'tis <hi>beſt</hi> for them.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:43846:50"/> Quod ſis, eſſe velis, nihilque malis.</q>
            <p>Believers ſhould never ſay, they had <hi>rather</hi> it might be <hi>otherwiſe</hi> with them; than <hi>God ſees it fit it ſhould</hi> be; when the Plough of Affliction pierces deepeſt, <hi>Light and Joy</hi> is ſowing; and the Hopes of what at laſt will be reaped, ſhould allay the Sorrow wherewith the ſowing is attended. The <hi>Grounds</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to afflicted Saints are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Gods <hi>goodneſs is unqueſtionable, howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he is pleaſed to deal with his People.</hi> Let them be <hi>plagued,</hi> let them be <hi>chaſtned never ſo ſore;</hi> yet <hi>God is good to</hi> Iſrael, <hi>even to them that are of a clean Heart,</hi> Pſal. 73. 1. God is <hi>their</hi> God, and his dealings are ever <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> to his <hi>Gracious Covenant.</hi> His wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, is not like the <hi>wounds</hi> given by an <hi>Enemy,</hi> but like the <hi>Chyrurgians Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings</hi> in order to <hi>greater ſoundneſs</hi> and for <hi>Lifes Preſervation,</hi> Iſa. 27. <hi>Hath he ſmitten him, as he ſmote thoſe that ſmote him?</hi> No no, great is the Difference between the <hi>Rod</hi> and the <hi>Scorpion;</hi> between Believers being <hi>chaſtned as Children;</hi> and the Wicked their <hi>falling into the hands of the Living God,</hi> who takes Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>good</hi> which Saints receive by Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is <hi>Spiritual.</hi> The <hi>Soul</hi> has a great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:43846:50"/> done to it. The <hi>Conſcience is bettered</hi> as to <hi>calmneſs</hi> and <hi>cleanneſs,</hi> the Heart is made more pure, the <hi>Spirit of the Lord</hi> works a greater change into the <hi>Image</hi> of God; ſo that there is an advancing from <hi>Glory to Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> When <hi>Job</hi> had been ſome while afflicted, his Spirit began to run more clear, <hi>Job</hi> 23. 10. <hi>But he knoweth the way that I take, when he hath tried me, I ſhall come forth like Gold.</hi> The <hi>Fire and Furnace</hi> in <hi>Zion purges</hi> the Droſs, and how then does the <hi>Gold ſhine!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That good which the Saints reap by Affliction, is <hi>peculiar and diſtinguiſhing.</hi> Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men are either ſtupid under Affliction; or if they are ſtartled; they return to their former Security after Affliction. To have <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction ſanctified</hi> is a favour <hi>peculiar</hi> to Gods <hi>peculiar People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This good which the Saints receive by Affliction at preſent, is <hi>an earneſt to them of Eternal good things in the other World.</hi> Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are part of the <hi>Purgatory,</hi> through which the Saints paſs and are made meet for Glory. The <hi>Popiſh Purgatory</hi> is a <hi>meer Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> for that Antichriſtian Churches <hi>ſecular Gain.</hi> The Dead find it to be nothing; but vaſt is the Worldly gain accrueing hereby to the <hi>living;</hi> by this <hi>Craft</hi> comes in the <hi>Prieſts Wealth.</hi> But the Purgatory of Affliction, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:43846:51"/> Purity, and is really Beneficial. The Rod at preſent yeilds the peaceable fruits of Righteouſneſs, and when <hi>theſe are brought forth</hi> a <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs</hi> is aſſured, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8.</p>
            <p>I have done with the <hi>firſt</hi> Doctrine, <hi>That Saints are afflicted for their good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall be Brief in the Second which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            <p>D. 2. The ſecond Doctrine, which I raiſed from the Text was this. <hi>The Rod of God is a means to make the Word of God to be the better Learned,</hi> Pſal. 119. 67. <hi>Before I was afflicted I went aſtray, but now have I kept thy Word.</hi> Affliction was the means to put a ſtop to the Pſalmiſts wandring; it brought his Feet into the <hi>right</hi> Path and <hi>eſtabliſhed his goings.</hi> What a <hi>light ſhines</hi> in the <hi>School</hi> of Affliction? Things are ſeen <hi>naked</hi> there! <hi>Sin;</hi> the <hi>World, Hell</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction;</hi> are all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. The <hi>great things</hi> of the Word, are plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen to be <hi>great</hi> and <hi>good indeed;</hi> and are no longer lookt upon as <hi>ſtrange things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this Doctrine, I ſhall,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shew you <hi>when the Word of God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed learned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:43846:51"/> 2. What <hi>influence the Rod of God has unto the better Learning of his Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Make <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Place, I am to ſhew you, <hi>when the Word of God is indeed and aright learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Learning the Word implies, <hi>a Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Words Divine Authority and Truth.</hi> He has not learned the Word, who does not believe it to be indeed the Word of God, who cannot lie, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>All Scripture is given by Inſpiration of God.</hi> Mens <hi>Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> to the Word are <hi>audacious</hi> and <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble falſhoods.</hi> And if <hi>Angels from Heaven</hi> ſhould ſpeak contrary to it, they muſt not have our <hi>Aſſent,</hi> but our <hi>Anathema,</hi> Gal. 1. 8. <hi>But though we or an Angel from Heaven, preach any other Goſpel unto you; than that which we have preached unto you; let him be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> They who have learned the Word of God, perceive the <hi>Harmony</hi> of all its <hi>parts;</hi> and believe the <hi>whole,</hi> and are <hi>influenced</hi> by that <hi>belief,</hi> for the certain Truth of the Word makes it moſt <hi>Encouraging</hi> and <hi>Comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to the <hi>Saints;</hi> and with what <hi>Sweet Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity</hi> do they <hi>reſt</hi> upon it! And the ſame Truth <hi>ſhould</hi> make it <hi>very Terrible</hi> to all <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Sinners!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:43846:52"/> 2. Learning the Word implies, <hi>an obſerving the Scope and Deſign of the Word of God;</hi> now the Deſign and Scope of it is, the <hi>Glory of God;</hi> and <hi>Mans Happineſs and Salvation.</hi> God cannot have an <hi>higher end</hi> in what he does, than <hi>Himſelf,</hi> for <hi>he</hi> is <hi>above all;</hi> therefore he has <hi>made</hi> and <hi>does all</hi> things <hi>for Himſelf;</hi> and truly ſince <hi>of him and through him are all things;</hi> he is worthy that all things ſhould be <hi>referred to him,</hi> and that in all things, he ſhould always be <hi>glorified,</hi> Rom. 11. 36. <hi>For of him, and through him, and to him are all things to whom be Glory for ever,</hi> Amen. In <hi>Subordination</hi> to his own Glory; the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns mans wellfare, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Glory be to God in the Higheſt, on Earth Peace, good will towards men.</hi> When the Word of God is truly learned; <hi>great notice is taken</hi> of its <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign;</hi> and the <hi>Learners aim</hi> is accordingly <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</hi> The <hi>Glory of God</hi> and <hi>mans trueſt good</hi> are <hi>inſeparably conjoined.</hi> So that this is paſt doubt, when man moſt Minds <hi>Gods Honour,</hi> he Minds moſt his <hi>own Intereſt and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Learning the Word, implies <hi>taking due notice of the Purity and Holineſs of the Word of God.</hi> Pſal. 12. 6. <hi>The Words of the Lord are pure Words, as! Silver tried in a Furnace of Earth purified ſeven times.</hi> The Pſalmiſt ſaw this Purity, and did not take offence at it,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:43846:52"/> but very much <hi>liked</hi> it, and <hi>loved</hi> the Word the <hi>better</hi> for it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 140. <hi>Thy Word is very pure; therefore thy Servant loveth it.</hi> God the Author of this Word is of <hi>Purer Eyes than to behold Iniquity;</hi> no wonder that the Word is purer <hi>than to allow of any Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> The Word will not permit Sin in the <hi>Tabernacle, Job</hi> 11. 14. <hi>If Iniquity be in thy Hand, put it far away, and let not wickedneſs dwell in thy Tabernacle.</hi> The Word prohibits <hi>our contentedly Suffering</hi> Sin to <hi>ly upon our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Levit. 19. 17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thy Heart; thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour; and not ſuffer Sin upon him.</hi> The <hi>hands</hi> muſt be cleanſed, and ſo muſt <hi>eſpecially</hi> the <hi>Heart,</hi> Jam. 4. 8. <hi>Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you, cleanſe your Hands ye Sinners, purifie your Hearts ye double minded.</hi> If Sin commands the <hi>Tongue,</hi> Religion is but vain; if Sin be regarded in the Heart, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is to no purpoſe. How excellent and pure is this Word of God! and thoſe that learn it ſee both the Neceſſity and Excellency of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Holineſs; and they <hi>hunger and thirſt,</hi> and <hi>follow after Righteouſneſs and true Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Learning the Word, implies <hi>beholding wondrous things in the Word of God,</hi> Pſal. 119. 18. <hi>Open thou my Eyes, that I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold wondrous things out of thy Law.</hi> And <hi>V.</hi> 129. <hi>Thy Teſtimonies are wonderful, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:43846:53"/> 
               <hi>doeth my Soul keep them.</hi> The <hi>Light</hi> which ſhines forth from hence, is <hi>marvellous,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 2. <hi>That ye ſhould ſhew forth the Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of him, who hath called you out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into marvellous Light.</hi> The <hi>Mercy</hi> is <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing;</hi> which ſaves from <hi>ſo much Sin;</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents <hi>no leſs</hi> than <hi>endleſs Miſery;</hi> and brings thoſe to <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> who <hi>deſerved to die the Eternal Death,</hi> Jud. <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Keep your ſelves in the Love of God, looking for the Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto Eternal Life.</hi> That <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> which appears in the contrivance of Mans Redemption by Chriſt the Mediator, is the Admiration of the <hi>elect Principalities and Powers,</hi> Eph. 3. 10. <hi>To the intent that now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee Principalities and Powers in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Places, might be known by the Church the manifold Wiſdom of God.</hi> And the <hi>Love of God in Chriſt,</hi> is moſt <hi>ſweetly aſtoniſhing!</hi> 'Tis without <hi>Motive,</hi> without <hi>Meaſure,</hi> without <hi>Alteration,</hi> its <hi>height</hi> and <hi>length</hi> and <hi>depth</hi> and <hi>breadth</hi> are paſt <hi>our reach</hi> and <hi>finding out.</hi> And how <hi>highly</hi> are thoſe who are intereſted in this Love, <hi>advanced!</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 1. <hi>Behold what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Love the Father hath beſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God!</hi> and all his Sons <hi>are heirs of Everlaſting Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Learning the Word, implies <hi>knowing the Truth as it is in Jeſus,</hi> Eph. 4. 20, 21. <hi>But ye have not ſo learned Chriſt; if ſo be that ye</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:43846:53"/> 
               <hi>have heard him, and been taught by him, as the Truth is in Jeſus.</hi> To know the Truth as it is in Jeſus, is to know <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> and all <hi>Divine Truths</hi> with <hi>reſpect to Chriſt.</hi> He is the <hi>Center</hi> in which <hi>all the Lines</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>meet.</hi> If God be lookt upon <hi>without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> to this <hi>Mediator;</hi> the remembrance of the <hi>Holy and Righteous and Almighty Jehovah;</hi> muſt needs be <hi>terrible and confounding</hi> to <hi>guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and defiled Sinners.</hi> But the Knowledge of God <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> is <hi>beneficial</hi> and <hi>reviving;</hi> for in Chriſt he is <hi>acceſſible,</hi> and a <hi>God in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> and how encouraging is the Knowledg of <hi>Duty;</hi> when we <hi>look to Jeſus,</hi> becauſe in Chriſt we have <hi>aſſiſting Grace</hi> to do it ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and when 'tis thus done, in <hi>Him</hi> we have acceptance, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>Ye alſo as lively ſtones are built up a Spiritual Houſe, an Holy Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to offer up Spiritual Sacrifices acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Though the <hi>Houſe be Spiritual;</hi> though the <hi>Prieſthood be Holy,</hi> though the <hi>Sacrifice be Spiritual;</hi> yet 'tis <hi>not upon their own,</hi> but upon the <hi>account of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that they are <hi>acceptable.</hi> Looking to Jeſus, we may look upon <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> without <hi>diſmay,</hi> nay with <hi>thankful Hearts,</hi> for He ſaves from <hi>both,</hi> and through <hi>him</hi> an <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant entrance is adminiſtred into the Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdom.</hi> He has not learned the Word to any purpoſe, who does <hi>not know</hi> that Chriſt <hi>is all in all,</hi> and <hi>fills all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:43846:54"/> 6. Learning the Word of God, implies <hi>feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Power and Efficacy of this Word;</hi> till the Spirit accompanies it and ſets it home up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Heart; and there is an experience of its Power; the Word is not aright learned. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Our Goſpel came to you, not in Word onely, but in Power alſo, and in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt and in much Aſſurance.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt made you ſenſible of the Goſpels Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, and its Efficacy aſſured you of its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity. So 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Ye received it not as the Word of men, but as it is in Truth the Word of God, which worketh effectually in you that believe.</hi> This Word ſhews its Power in <hi>pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down ſtrong holds, in caſting down Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the Knowledg of God; and in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoughts into Captivity and Obedience to Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 4, 5. The Spirit of God wrought <hi>Signs and Wonders and divers Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, according to his own Will;</hi> for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Goſpel when firſt it was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the World; and theſe were <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Spirit's Demonſtration</hi> of its <hi>Truth.</hi> And <hi>Miracles</hi> in the <hi>New Creation</hi> ceaſe not to be <hi>wrought ſtill</hi> by the <hi>ſame Spirit.</hi> The Word is made an effectual means, to make the <hi>dead in Sin alive to God,</hi> to make the <hi>Blind to ſee,</hi> and the <hi>Lame to walk in the Way of Gods Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:43846:54"/> 7. Learning the Word, implies a <hi>ready and Hearty embracing, what the Word of God Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers and Promiſes.</hi> Mammon and Satan make but <hi>very poor and mean offers</hi> and their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are deceitful,</hi> they can offer nothing but what is temporal, the things they boaſt of are onely good in appearance; and they quickly vaniſh away. Indeed there is ſomething that is <hi>Eternal,</hi> but 'tis <hi>Eternal Wo and Miſery,</hi> that abides the worldly and the wicked; but this Satan ſtudiouſly endeavours to conceal from them. Whereas the offers of the Goſpel are great and glorious, worthy of all accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by all to be accepted; the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes here are <hi>ſo firm,</hi> that they ſhall <hi>remain,</hi> when <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away,</hi> Pſal. 119. 152. <hi>Concerning thy Teſtimonies, I have known of old, that thou haſt founded them for ever.</hi> If the Children of men might <hi>have their wiſh,</hi> and would <hi>wiſh but wiſely;</hi> they would wiſh, for what the Word aſſures to all Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepters of it. Here is juſtifying Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the guilty and Condemned; here is Healing, Sanctifying Grace for the Diſeaſed and Defiled; here is Strength for the Weak, and Comfort for them that are caſt down; and for loſt Souls great and Everlaſting Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How can he be ſaid to have learned the Word of God; or to know when he is well offer'd; by whom ſuch offers are refuſed?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:43846:55"/> 8. Learning the Word, implies the <hi>Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Conformity of the whole man to the commands of the Word of God.</hi> Promiſes and Priviledges are to be ſtudied and embraced; and Precepts and Commands are to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. He that <hi>caſts the commands behind his back,</hi> is very <hi>Preſumptuous</hi> in <hi>applying Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to himſelf.</hi> That Hope will make a man aſhamed, which is not accompanied with Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Hearken to the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 166, 167, 168. <hi>Lord I have hoped for thy Salvation, and done thy Commandments. My Soul hath kept thy Teſtimonies, and I love them exceedingly, I have kept thy Precepts and thy Teſtimonies, for all my ways are before Thee.</hi> He that has learned the Word of God, knows that <hi>the Law is not made void by Faith, but eſtabliſhed,</hi> Rom. 3. 31. <hi>Do we then by Faith, make void the Law, through Faith? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, yea we eſtabliſh the Law,</hi> Chriſt the Churches Head and Prophet, in his Sermon upon the Mount, ſhews the extent of the Law, requiring Purity in the Heart and Thoughts, as well as in the Life and Actions, condemns them <hi>who ſhall break the leaſt of theſe Commands and ſhall teach men ſo;</hi> but thoſe that <hi>teach and do them, he owns as great in his Kingdom,</hi> Mat. 5. 19. The Law ſpoken from <hi>Mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai</hi> is eſtabliſhed by the Legiſlator Chriſt, in <hi>Mount Sion</hi> as a <hi>Rule of Righteouſneſs.</hi> And they who are rightly inſtructed, <hi>which walk</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:43846:55"/> 
               <hi>according to this Rule,</hi> both <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> will be order'd according to its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and <hi>Peace and Mercy will be upon them,</hi> and hereby they ſhew themſelves indeed the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Learning the Word, implies a <hi>living in Expectation and Hope of that Glory which God in his Word has revealed,</hi> Rom. 5. 2. <hi>By whom we have acceſs by Faith into this Grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſtand, and rejoice in Hope of the Glory of God.</hi> The Apoſtle tells that our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt hath <hi>aboliſhed Death, and hath brought Life and Immortality to light by the Goſpel.</hi> What Joy is ſet before us to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage patient continuance in Faith and well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing! Were it not for this; the <hi>Diſciples of Chriſt would be of all men moſt miſerable:</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 19. But ſince the <hi>Glory hoped</hi> for is ſo <hi>ſure</hi> and <hi>near;</hi> they are the <hi>onely Happy ones</hi> in the World. He that learned the Word aright, Heaven is in his Eye; there is his Heart and Treaſure. He knows he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perfectly Holy or Happy, till he come thither; and when once come there; Holineſs and Happineſs will be perfect in degree; and endleſs in Duration. Nothing therefore can <hi>move him away from the Hope of the Goſpel.</hi> He abides in the Word, and the Word in him; and <hi>ſtands faſt in the Lord himſelf,</hi> and at laſt receives the bleſſed Life that is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 24, 25. <hi>Let that therefore abide</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:43846:56"/> 
               <hi>in you which ye have heard from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; if that which ye have heard from the beginning ſhall remain in you; ye alſo ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Son and in the Father; and this is the Promiſe that he hath Promiſed us, even Eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if <hi>all this</hi> be implied in <hi>Learning the Word of God;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many may <hi>Conſcience</hi> reproach for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver having learned the Word to this day! <hi>Strangers</hi> they are to its <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>haters</hi> of its <hi>Purity,</hi> and moſt fooliſhly and wickedly neglect that Grace and Salvation, which is there tender'd to them!</p>
            <p>How many may <hi>Sigh for Sorrow,</hi> that they have learned the Word of God <hi>no better!</hi> that their Faith is no ſtronger, their delight in the Word of God no greater! and that there are ſo many defects in their Obedience to it!</p>
            <p>How ſhould we all <hi>groan</hi> with <hi>earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,</hi> that <hi>God Himſelf</hi> would be our <hi>Teacher,</hi> and make us <hi>right Learners</hi> of his Word! And if <hi>He</hi> is pleaſed to teach us, how Bleſſed, Holy, and Wiſe will his teaching make us! and <hi>ſuch</hi> alſo we ſhall <hi>continue;</hi> for that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will have a laſting effect upon us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 33, <hi>Teach me O Lord the Way of thy Statutes, and I ſhall keep it unto the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:43846:56"/>
            <p> In the ſecond Place, I am to ſhew the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence,</hi> that the <hi>Rod of God</hi> has to make his <hi>Word the better Learned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Rod of Affliction <hi>awakens the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> So that it is very punctual in doing its Office; Conſcience being ſtartled cauſes <hi>fear;</hi> Where there was too much <hi>unconcernedneſs</hi> and <hi>ſtupidity</hi> before. The Conſciences of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs Brethren</hi> after the great Injury they did him; lay in a deep ſleep for many Years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; but Diſtreſs and Affliction awakened them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. 21. <hi>They ſaid one to another, We are verily guilty concerning our Brother, in that we ſaw the anguiſh of his Soul, when he beſought us, and we would not hear; therefore is this diſtreſs come upon us.</hi> Conſcience being awakened is full of remorſe, becauſe the Word of God has been obſerved with no more care. Conſcience alſo is ſtill urging, <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſtimony.</hi> This is the way to be freed from Trouble, and to attain to Peace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 165. <hi>Great Peace have they that Love thy Law.</hi> Gal. 6. 16. <hi>And as many as walk according to this Rule, Peace be on them, and Mercy, and upon the</hi> Iſrael <hi>of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Rod of Affliction, <hi>takes off from worldly Buſineſs and Diverſions;</hi> and hereupon they that are afflicted, <hi>are at better leaſure to conſider their ways,</hi> Eccleſ. 7. 14. <hi>In the day of</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:43846:57"/> 
               <hi>Adverſity conſider.</hi> God is not to be <hi>complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of</hi> for <hi>puniſhing</hi> Sin; but men who are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ſhould <hi>ſearch and try their ways and turn to Him.</hi> Lam. 3. 39, 40. <hi>Inconſiderateneſs</hi> is ſpoken of, as the occaſion of a World of Wickedneſs, and 'tis exclaimed againſt as very offenſive and inexcuſable, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 2, 3. <hi>Hear O Heavens and give ear O Earth, for the Lord hath ſpoken; I have nouriſhed and brought up Children, and they have rebelled againſt me; The Ox knows his owner, and the Aſs his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Crib, but</hi> Iſrael <hi>doth not know, my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doth not conſider!</hi> Now the more any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what they do; the greater heed they will take to the Word of God; for this Word Counſels ſafely; it directs and leads in the way of Peace and Truth, and Life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 23. <hi>For the Commandment is a Lamp, and the Law is Light, and Reproofs of Inſtruction are the way of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Rod of Affliction <hi>brings God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, whoſe the Word is;</hi> and God being remembred, his Word is the more awfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. Moſt men forget the Lord all their days, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 32. <hi>Can a Maid forget her Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments? or a Bride her attire? yet my People have forgotten me days without number.</hi> And forgetting the <hi>Lord</hi> they forget <hi>themſelves,</hi> their <hi>Duty</hi> and their <hi>Intereſt.</hi> Affliction is a means to bring God to mind; and his hand being lifted up, and there being a Rod in his
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:43846:57"/> hand; there is a more heedful looking into his Word to know his Pleaſure, and what is the ground of his preſent diſpleaſure and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie. <hi>Job</hi> was deſirous to <hi>know his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion and Sin;</hi> and wherefore it <hi>was that God hid his Face and counted him for his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy,</hi> Job 13. 23, 24.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Rod of Affliction, brings <hi>Iniquity to remembrance, which is contrary to the Word of God.</hi> The very <hi>firſt ſtroke</hi> of Correction, how of a ſudden has it <hi>opened mens Eyes,</hi> and <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall'd</hi> their <hi>Sins</hi> more <hi>terrible than an Army with Banners</hi> before them! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 21. <hi>I will reprove thee and ſet them in Order before thine Eyes.</hi> Now the remembrance of Sin is a great ingredient in true Contrition and Repentance, which the Word of God ſo often calls for, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 31. <hi>Then ſhall ye remember your evil ways, and doings that have not been good, and ſhall loath your ſelves in your own ſight for your Iniquities and Abominations.</hi> To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Sin in <hi>Hell,</hi> will be to remember Sin <hi>too late;</hi> and the <hi>Eternal Remembrance</hi> of it, and the <hi>Folly and Perverſeneſs</hi> in giving way to it; will be a <hi>great part</hi> of the Sinners <hi>Eternal Torment.</hi> But to remember Sin, <hi>in Affliction;</hi> is very profitable; how evident now is the deceitfulneſs of it! All its pretences of Impunity, Gain, and Pleaſure; are found alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vain. This is <hi>One great Leſſon</hi> of the Rod. <hi>Sin cheats all its Servants, and quickly ends in Sorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:43846:58"/> 5. The Rod of Affliction, brings <hi>Duty to remembrance, which the Word of God requires.</hi> Omiſſion and neglect of Duty, and negligence in Duty, are then reflected on with grief; for if Duty had been more ſeriouſly and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently performed, poſſibly the ſtroke <hi>might not have been felt;</hi> and ſuppoſe <hi>it had;</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of Ordinances might have furniſhed the Heart with <hi>more Faith and Patience to have born it.</hi> And now <hi>ſays the Rod</hi> be <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acquainted with the Word,</hi> know thy Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and from what <hi>Principle</hi> thou art to act; after what <hi>manner,</hi> and to what <hi>end.</hi> Act from Spiritual Life, let Faith work by Love; and the more there is of the Heart and will, in Obedience; 'tis the better; and let it be the conſtant deſign, that <hi>God in all things may be glorified through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 11. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction vehemently urges unto practical God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and unto walking in newneſs of Life. <hi>Doers of the Word are bleſſed in their deed,</hi> whereas thoſe Profeſſours are <hi>Self-deceivers,</hi> who ſatisfie themſelves with a <hi>Faith which Works not,</hi> but <hi>is dead,</hi> Jam. 1. 22. <hi>But be ye doers of the Word, and not hears only deceiving your own ſelves.</hi> V. 25. <hi>Whoſo looketh into the perfect Law of Liberty, and continueth therein, he being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the Work; this man ſhall be bleſſed in his deed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:43846:58"/> 6. The Rod of Affliction <hi>brings Death to remembrance,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> brings the <hi>Night,</hi> when the <hi>Work,</hi> which the Word of God calls for, <hi>can be done no more,</hi> Joh. 9. 4. <hi>I muſt work the Works of him that ſent me while 'tis day, the night cometh when no man can work:</hi> When a man ſeriouſly meditates on Death, how <hi>wiſe</hi> will it make him! he will number his days aright, and do the Work for which time and days are given him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 12. <hi>Teach us ſo to number our days, that we may apply our Hearts to Wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if Death be brought to remembrance by Affliction; <hi>Judgment</hi> which follows at the heels of Death will alſo be thought of. And this Judgment will be according to the Word of God, for this Book among others will be opened at the great day; and Sentence paſs'd according to it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 48. <hi>The Word which I have ſpoken the ſame ſhall judge him at the laſt day.</hi> The Conſideration of a future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment how will it <hi>quicken</hi> to the <hi>ſtudy, ſearch,</hi> and Practiſe of the Word! If the Word now <hi>bind</hi> thee, becauſe of thy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief and Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency</hi> in Sin; thou art <hi>bound in Heaven.</hi> If the Word <hi>now condemns</hi> thee; continuing as thou art; the <hi>Judge</hi> alſo will moſt certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thee. But if the <hi>Word</hi> at preſent does <hi>acquit</hi> thee, the <hi>Judge</hi> alſo will <hi>abſolve</hi> thee. If the Word pronounces thee bleſſed, becauſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:43846:59"/> 
               <hi>Poor in Spirit, Meek, a Mourner for Sin, one that hungers and thirſts after Righteouſneſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe pure in Heart, a Peace-maker, and one that is willing to ſuffer Perſecution for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſake; rather than ceaſe the Practice of Righteouſneſs,</hi> Mat. 5. 3, 10. Being thus pronounced Bleſſed by the Word; Our Lord will never contradict himſelf; but at laſt will ſay to thee, <hi>Come thou Bleſſed of my Father inherit the Kingdom prepared for thee from the Foundation of the World,</hi> Mat. 25. 34.</p>
            <p>I come in the <hi>laſt place</hi> to the <hi>Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE I. Of <hi>Information:</hi> From the Doctrine we may learn ſeveral uſeful Leſſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may be inſtructed concerning the <hi>end</hi> of Affliction, <hi>which is our truer Knowledg and Holineſs.</hi> The <hi>Rod ſends</hi> us to the <hi>Word,</hi> from whence <hi>Wiſdom</hi> comes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. 6. <hi>For the Lord giveth Wiſdom, out of his Mouth cometh Knowledg and Underſtanding.</hi> And this Word is the Word not onely of Wiſdom but of <hi>Grace</hi> alſo; a means to work, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it; until 'tis perfected in Glory, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 32. <hi>And now Brethren I commend you to God and to the Word of his Grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among all them that are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:43846:59"/> 2. God is very <hi>much provoked when his Word is contemned;</hi> therefore he afflicts that his Word may be regarded; ſurely then a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard to it angers him. 'Tis great Condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion in God to ſpeak to man; 'tis great kindneſs to ſpeak to man for his own good; but when man ſhall neither regard his own good, nor the Lords condeſcending kindneſs; this very much incenſes God againſt him. The Apoſtles Caution is very ſtrict, and with a great deal of Reaſon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 25. <hi>See that ye refuſe not him that ſpeaketh; for if they eſcaped not who refuſed him that ſpake on Earth; much more ſhall not we eſcape, if we turn away from Him that ſpeaketh from Heaven.</hi> When lighter Afflictions are ineffectual to make men ſtand in awe of the Word of God; deſolating Judgments many times follow, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. 16. <hi>But they mocked the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of God, and deſpiſed his Words, and miſuſed his Prophets, until the Wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his People, till there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. When God is very angry; a <hi>believing Subjection to his Word is the way to have his Wrath appeaſed.</hi> Indeed nothing ſatisfies the Juſtice of God, but Chriſts Sacrifice of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon the Croſs for Sin; nothing Merits the favour of God; but the Obedience and Sufferings of his Dear Son. But yet Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:43846:60"/> to the Word of God, is like taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the fewel from the fire, whereby the fire is extinguiſhed, when according to the Word, we ceaſe to do evil, and learn to doi well; the ground of Gods controverſie is at an end. It was a dreadful Propheſie, <hi>yet forty days and</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> This Word was believed, and as it was a loud call to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo that call was anſwered and obeyed; it iſſued well, the <hi>Ninevites</hi> repent of their wickedneſs, God repents of his Anger, and does not pour it upon them, <hi>Jon.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>And God ſaw their Works, that they turned from their evil ways; and God repented of the evil that he had ſaid, that he would do unto them, and did it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. When God <hi>lets Sinners alone in a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked neglect of his Word, without afflicting them, 'tis to be feared, he intends they ſhall dy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Wiſdom.</hi> Gods <hi>forbearing to afflict;</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an Argument of <hi>great diſpleaſure,</hi> Iſa. 1. 5. <hi>Why ſhould ye be ſtricken any more? ye will ſtill revolt more and more.</hi> And being ſtricken no more, they are the more hardned from his fear; till at laſt <hi>as Fiſhes are taken in an evil Net; and as Birds are caught in the Snare;</hi> ſo theſe Sinners <hi>are ſnared in an evil time; when it falleth ſuddenly upon them.</hi> Eccleſ. 9. 12.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Saints which <hi>are not exerciſed with Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:43846:60"/> had need to be very careful, <hi>that gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler methods which are uſed, be effectual to their Progreſs in Grace and Holineſs.</hi> 'Tis found <hi>harder</hi> to know how <hi>to abound,</hi> than <hi>how to want;</hi> more difficult to avoid the Snares of Proſperity, than to overcome the Temptations of Adverſity. Hence that Caution, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 10, 11. <hi>When thou haſt eaten and art full, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that thou forget not the Lord thy God, in not keeping his Commandments, and his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his Statutes which I command thee this day.</hi> If you ſeldom feel the Rod; but onely fair means are uſed; Oh admire Divine goodneſs, and with great care take heed to his Word, being very thankful and fruitful together. And if in the <hi>height of Proſperity,</hi> where neither <hi>frown</hi> is ſeen in <hi>Gods face,</hi> nor <hi>blow felt</hi> from his <hi>hand,</hi> He is with <hi>Joy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred and ſerved;</hi> this Obedience is with great <hi>evidence</hi> of <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Uprightneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Saints who <hi>after feel the Rod of Affliction ſhould have a more than ordinary regard to the Word of God.</hi> They <hi>ſhould tremble at it,</hi> for God has a ſpecial <hi>regard to them that tremble at his Word,</hi> Iſa. 66. 2. And they ſhould <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice with trembling; in it.</hi> Saints who are frequently chaſtiſed, are intruſted with the more Talents, and ſhould improve them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. Another day we ſhall be called to account, what <hi>Benefit we have received by Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions;</hi> as well as <hi>how we have profited under</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:43846:61"/> 
               <hi>Ordinances.</hi> Frequent Troubles ſhould make our <hi>Conſciences more tender,</hi> Sin by the <hi>blows</hi> of the Rod ſhould be <hi>ſtruck more dead;</hi> we ſhould live more as <hi>Pilgrims on Earth,</hi> our <hi>Eye</hi> ſhould be <hi>more</hi> upon the <hi>Heavenly Inheritance;</hi> and the <hi>Apple of our Eye</hi> ſhould not be kept with greater <hi>charineſs,</hi> than we keep the <hi>Word of God,</hi> Prov. 7. 2. <hi>Keep my Commandments and live, and my Law as the Apple of thine Eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE II. Of <hi>Counſel</hi> to All to <hi>incline their Ears and apply their Hearts to learn the Word of God.</hi> That you may attain to <hi>this Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (incomparably the trueſt and beſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the World) is the deſign of <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and you ſee 'tis the deſign of <hi>Afflicting Providences.</hi> And Mercies are beſtowed with the ſame intent, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 45. All the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances wrought for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God wrought them to this end, <hi>That they might obſerve his Statutes, and keep his Laws.</hi> That Wiſdom, which is to be found in the Word of God, is a <hi>Treaſure</hi> more <hi>valuable</hi> than all the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures on Earth;</hi> and this Treaſure <hi>lies deep;</hi> but 'tis highly <hi>worth ſearching</hi> for. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Solomon</hi> ſignifies to us, that we ſhould <hi>ſeek for it, as for Silver, and ſearch for it as for hid Treaſures,</hi> Prov. 2. 4. <hi>If thou ſeekeſt her as Silver, and ſearcheſt for her as for hid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; then ſhalt thou underſtand the fear of the Lord and find the Knowledge of God.</hi> Nay
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:43846:61"/> this Word of God is not only your <hi>Treaſure;</hi> but 'tis as much as <hi>your Life</hi> is worth, to neglect this Word of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 46, 47. <hi>Set your Hearts unto all the Words, which I teſtifie among you this day, for it is not a vain thing for you, for it is your Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I ſhall anſwer two Queſtions, and ſo conclude this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is, <hi>Which Way this Learning in the Word of God may be attained?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is, <hi>What are ſufficient and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Evidences; that the Word of God is truly Learned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> Queſtion is, <hi>Which Way this Learning in the Word of God may be attained?</hi> Unto this I Anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let every <hi>Rod you feel cauſe a ſtricter ſearch into the Word.</hi> 'Tis part of the Rods Language, <hi>Tolle, lege;</hi> take the Word, and Read, and be better acquainted with it. The Rod is uſed in Grammar Schools; that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors there may be more diligently Studied. God uſes <hi>his</hi> Rod in his own School; that <hi>his Book</hi> the <hi>Holy Bible</hi> may be the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and practiſed. There is not <hi>any Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> but it <hi>ought</hi> to be lookt upon as an <hi>Admonition</hi> to take greater heed to the <hi>Holy</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:43846:62"/> 
               <hi>Scripture, which is profitable for Doctrine, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, for Correction, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, that the Man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be ſenſible, that <hi>true and ſaving Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is from above, therefore ask it from thence,</hi> Jam. 1. 5. <hi>If any of you lack Wiſdom, let him ask it of God; who gives to all men liberally without upbraiding; and it ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him.</hi> And <hi>V.</hi> 17. <hi>Every good and perfect Gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of Lights.</hi> And as God is the Father of Lights, ſo his Spirit is the Spirit of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Revelation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 17, 18. He <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens the Eyes of the Underſtanding,</hi> and puts ſaving Knowledge into the Heart. What an <hi>Inſtructer</hi> is the <hi>Spirit of the Lord!</hi> He not onely reveals Gods Counſel; but gives an Heart to apprehend it, and to be anſwerably affected with it. He not onely <hi>ſpeaks the Word,</hi> which it does ſo infinitely concern all to know; but he gives alſo the <hi>Ear to hear,</hi> the <hi>Eye to ſee,</hi> and the <hi>Heart to underſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Reſolve when <hi>Inſtructed to Praiſe your Inſtructer;</hi> thus does the Pſalmiſt Purpoſe and Promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 7. <hi>I will Praiſe thee, with uprightneſs of Heart, when I ſhall have learned thy Righteous Judgments.</hi> How joyful was the Hallelujah! when the Pſalmiſt had ſaid; <hi>He geveth his Word unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>his Statutes and</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:43846:62"/> 
               <hi>his Judgments to the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147. 19, 20. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 164. <hi>Seven times a day do I Praiſe thee, becauſe of thy Righteous Judgments.</hi> And <hi>V.</hi> 62. He had ſaid, upon the ſame account, he would <hi>ariſe at midnight and give thanks</hi> unto God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Look unto <hi>Jeſus in whom are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge,</hi> Col. 2. 3. Chriſt is the Churches Lawgiver and Prophet. He declares the Father, whom no man at any time hath ſeen, and <hi>no man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Father, but the Son, and he to whom the Son ſhall reveal him,</hi> Mat. 11. 17. He opens the Eyes and <hi>Underſtanding to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Scripture, Luk.</hi> 24. 45. The Goſpel is as it were a Sealed Book, till he opens it; a right underſtanding of <hi>the Things of God,</hi> and which <hi>belong to your Peace,</hi> is both Chriſts Purchaſe; and the Work and <hi>Effect of his il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminating Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Pray much for <hi>Meekneſs and Humility; and let not any deceitful luſt be harboured in the Heart.</hi> A Promiſe of Guidance is made to the Meek and Lowly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. 8, 9. <hi>Good and upright is the Lord, therefore will he teach Sinners in the way, the Meek will he guide in Judgment, and the Meek will he teach his Way.</hi> Make no Proviſion for any fleſhly or wordly Luſts, for theſe <hi>Luſts</hi> of the <hi>Heart</hi> influence the <hi>Head;</hi> and hinder the Light from ſhining
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:43846:63"/> there ſo clearly and powerfully, both <hi>Mind and Conſcience</hi> by fulfilling theſe Luſts will be <hi>defiled.</hi> The Apoſtle plainly intimates, that <hi>the old man muſt be put off which is corrupt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to deceitful Luſts; or elſe we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be renewed in the Spirit of our Mind,</hi> Eph. 4. 22, 23. In ſhort, be willing to know the Truth, that you may be ſanctified by the Truth. Look into the <hi>perfect Law of Liberty;</hi> and count you, walk <hi>moſt at Liberty;</hi> when you walk moſt <hi>accurately and exactly</hi> according to this Law. Cry for Knowledge in Order to Affection and Practiſe; that's the Way, to attain to great underſtanding in the Word of Righteouſneſs. Talents you ſhall ſtill be intruſted with, when you are thus ready to Trade with them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> Queſtion follows, <hi>What are ſufficient and comfortable Evidences, that the Word of God is truly Learned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What has been ſpoken already may be in part an Anſwer to this Queſtion. But that this great Caſe may be more fully reſolved; I ſhall add theſe Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You have truly Learned the Word of God, when <hi>you ſtand in awe of it.</hi> When Conſcience does urge, and the whole man does reverence the Words Authority. And the Heart concludes, that <hi>God muſt be obeyed what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:43846:63"/> 
               <hi>come on't,</hi> and that <hi>nothing can excuſe diſobedience to his Commands.</hi> This Holy awe of the Word muſt <hi>break the force</hi> of the ſtrongeſt Temptations from worldly Gain, and ſinful Pleaſures; and it muſt <hi>Swallow up the fear of the greateſt Men,</hi> who will diſlike you for the ſake of Righteouſneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 161. <hi>Princes have perſecuted me without a cauſe; but my Heart ſtandeth in awe of thy Word.</hi> Princes commands and threats are not ſo much to be minded, as Gods commands, and the threatnings wherewith they are enforced. When Princes have inflicted Temporal Death; they are come to their <hi>Ne plus ultra,</hi> they can go no further; Eternal Life and Death are not in their Power; but how is God to be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and dreaded, who can reward, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh for ever in the World to come!</p>
            <p n="2">2. You have truly Learned the Word of God, <hi>when you preferr it before all things, which are really of leſs value.</hi> Worldly Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Riches, Might, and earthly Greatneſs, are very deſpicable, compared with that Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, which this Word is a means to convey to us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 23, 24. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, let not the wiſe man Glory in his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, neither let the mighty man Glory in his Might; let not the rich man Glory in his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. But let him that glorieth, Glory in this, that he underſtandeth and knoweth Me.</hi> See how the Policy of the greateſt Potentates on
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:43846:64"/> Earth is diſparaged in Compariſon of Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Wiſdom, and not without ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The Policy of Princes, and themſelves periſh together. But Believers who are made wiſe by the Word of God, do mind, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto, and ſhall be unmoveably poſſeſs't of, an Eternal Glory and Kingdom, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6, 7. <hi>Howbeit we ſpeak Wiſdom among them that are perfect, yet not the Wiſdom of this World, nor of the Princes of this World, which come to nought; but we ſpeak the Wiſdom of God in a Myſtery; even the hidden Wiſdom, which God ordained before the World unto our Glory.</hi> In my Text the Pſalmiſt having ſaid, <hi>'Tis good for me that I have been afflicted,</hi> preſently expreſſes his Eſtimation of the Word, above thouſands of Gold and Silver. If the Word has an <hi>higher Room in your Judgments and Affections</hi> after Affliction, Affliction has <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly done you good,</hi> and you have learned the Word to good purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You have truly Learned the Word of God; <hi>if you Love and Delight therein, and make it your continual Meditation,</hi> Pſal. 119. 15, 16. <hi>I will Meditate in thy Precepts and have reſpect unto thy Ways, I will delight my ſelf in thy Statutes, I will not forget thy Word.</hi> Here are <hi>excellent Rules,</hi> and they that walk by them are <hi>perfected more and more;</hi> for they become <hi>more gloriouſly like to God himſelf;</hi> here are <hi>clean</hi> and <hi>ſafe</hi> Ways; Promiſes of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:43846:64"/> the <hi>good things of Time,</hi> ſo <hi>far as they are good for any of you;</hi> and of the <hi>infinitely better things of Eternity.</hi> All this may be well mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great delight. The more you love the Word, the greater will be your Peace, and you will hold on in the beſt ways without offence or ſtumbling, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 165. <hi>Great Peace have they that love thy Law, and nothing ſhall offend them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. You have truly learned the Word of God, when you <hi>keep it both in Heart and Life.</hi> Not to keep it in the Life, is a <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous contempt of the Word;</hi> not to keep it in the Heart, though there be a ſpecious form and ſhew of Religion, is but <hi>demure and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Hypocriſie.</hi> If the Word be in your Hearts, how will it as <hi>nouriſhing Food well concocted there</hi> make you <hi>ſtrong in Spirit!</hi> It will make your Hearts both <hi>clean</hi> and <hi>comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,</hi> and as a <hi>powerful Antidote</hi> expel <hi>Sins Poyſon,</hi> Pſal. 119. 11. <hi>Thy Word have I hid in my Heart, that I might not Sin againſt Thee.</hi> Let not Sin, but the <hi>Word Reign in your Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Body,</hi> that none of the Members of it may be defiled and debaſed in wicked Works and Services. Prize all the Ordinances and Inſtitutions of the Word of God; <hi>neglect</hi> none; be <hi>negligent</hi> in none. The more theſe are prized and uſed, the greater Reaſon you will ſee to perſiſt in the uſe of them, for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſpiritual Benefit will ſenſibly be reaped.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:43846:65"/> That Noble Pair, had learned the Word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, of whom it was ſaid, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>And they were both righteous before God, walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. You have truly learned the Word of God, when your <hi>care is to commend it and to adorn it in all things.</hi> The more this Word is in your Mouths, the more Edifying will your Diſcourſe be. Speak much <hi>of</hi> this Word and <hi>for</hi> it, nay if you ſpeak much of it as it is; you will ſpeak for it, for the Word will <hi>commend it ſelf.</hi> Mind thoſe Injunctions, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 29. <hi>Let no corrupt Communication pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of your Mouths, but that which is good to the uſe of Edifying, and which may adminiſter Grace to the hearers.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6, 7. <hi>Theſe Words, which I command thee this day, ſhall be in thy Heart; and thou ſhalt talk of them, when thou ſitteſt in thy Houſe; and when thou walkeſt by the way; when thou lieſt down; and when thou riſeſt up.</hi> How can it be ſaid the Word has been entertained in <hi>your</hi> Hearts; if you are not ready to commend it that it may have a Room in the Hearts of <hi>others?</hi> And let not your Commendation of the Word be <hi>verbal</hi> onely but <hi>real.</hi> Let your Converſations ever become the Goſpel, Live ſuirably to ſuch a pure, Holy and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Word, and <hi>walk worthy of God</hi> who by this Word <hi>has called you to his Kingdom and Glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Theſ. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:43846:65"/> 6. You have truly learned the Word of God, <hi>when you do every things by its Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> not onely your Duty towards God, but your Duty towards Man. In <hi>all your ways, God</hi> is to be eyed and <hi>acknowledged,</hi> that by his Word your <hi>Paths may be directed,</hi> Prov. 3. 6. <hi>Trade</hi> muſt be managed by the Word, and the rules of Truth and Juſtice and Equity laid down there; this is the way to <hi>grow Rich</hi> with a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> and without the <hi>Addition of Sorrow.</hi> A <hi>Family</hi> muſt be order'd by this Word; and all the Members of Families, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of them, muſt learn their Relative Duties from the Word of God. <hi>Recreations</hi> muſt be regulated hereby, elſe there may quickly be a forgetting of God, an exceſſive de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in them; and too great an expence of precious time. <hi>Nothing can be well done, if the Word be not regarded in the doing of it,</hi> and <hi>nothing can be ill done or miſcarry, under the Words Conduct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. You have truly learned the Word of God, <hi>if you never depart from it.</hi> Perſevering in Obedience will prove you <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Diſciples,</hi> Joh. 8. 31. <hi>Jeſus ſaid to thoſe</hi> Jews, <hi>who believed in him; if ye continue in my Word, then are ye my Diſciples indeed.</hi> This ſhews the Lord himſelf has been your Teacher, and is teaching you ſtill and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you together, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 33. <hi>Teach me O</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:43846:66"/> 
               <hi>Lord the way of thy Statutes, and I ſhall keep it to the end.</hi> And <hi>V.</hi> 102. he ſays, <hi>I have not departed from thy Judgments for thou haſt taught me.</hi> Stick unto <hi>his Teſtimonies,</hi> and <hi>cleave unto the Lord</hi> with ſuch a Reſolution as neither Mammon, Sin, nor Satan may ever <hi>ſhake.</hi> You can never change your Lord or his Service, but you muſt change <hi>infinitely for the worſe;</hi> therefore be <hi>ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, always abounding in his work.</hi> Though the <hi>Mountains depart, and the Hills be removed;</hi> yet do you <hi>abide with God,</hi> and <hi>ſtand faſt in the Faith unto the Death;</hi> that you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Promiſed <hi>Crown of Life,</hi> and wear it for evermore.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 49. <hi>line</hi> 16. <hi>for</hi> broken <hi>read</hi> troden, <hi>p.</hi> 53. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>f.</hi> in <hi>r.</hi> as, <hi>p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>f.</hi> the <hi>r.</hi> yet, <hi>p.</hi> 64. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>f.</hi> diligent <hi>r.</hi> vigilant, <hi>p.</hi> 76. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>f.</hi> undenied <hi>r.</hi> underived, <hi>p.</hi> 77. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>f.</hi> Tabb <hi>r.</hi> Fable.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:66"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for, and ſold by</hi> Tho. Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns <hi>in</hi> Cheapſide, <hi>near</hi> Mercers <hi>Chappel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Body of practical Divinity conſiſting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 176 Sermons on the leſſer Catechiſm compoſed by the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with a Supplement of ſome Sermons on ſeveral Texts of Scripture, by <hi>Tho. Watſon</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Miniſter of St. <hi>Stephens Walbrook,</hi> Printed from his own hand writing, recommended by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Miniſters to Maſters of Families and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Synodicon in Gallia Reformata,</hi> or the Acts, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, Deciſions, Canons of the Reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in <hi>France.</hi> Being 1. A moſt faithful and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Hiſtory of the riſe, growth, perfection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the Reformation in that Kingdom, with its fatal Cataſtrophe upon the revocation of the Edict at <hi>Nants</hi> in the year 1685. 2. The Confeſſion of Faith and Diſcipline of thoſe Churches. 3. A Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Speeches, Letters, Sacred Politicks, Caſes of Conſcience, and Controverſies in Divinity deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and reſolved by thoſe Grave Aſſemblies. 4. Many excellent expedients for preventing and healing Schiſms in the Churches and for re-uniting the diſmembred Body of divided Proteſtants. 5. The Laws, Government and Maintenance of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Univerſities, and Miniſters, together, with their Exerciſe of Diſcipline upon delinquent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Church Members. 6. A Record of very many illuſtrious Events of Divine Providence rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:43846:67"/> to thoſe Churches. The whole collected and compoſed out of the Original Manuſcript Acts of thoſe renowned Synods, a work never before extant in any Language, in two Vol. by <hi>John Quick,</hi> &amp;c. Fol.</p>
            <p>The Sure Mercies of <hi>David:</hi> Or, a Second Part of Heart-treaſure. Wherein is contained the ſum and ſubſtance of Goſpel-mercies purchaſed by Chriſt, and Promiſed in the Covenant of Grace, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſeveral ways how they are made ſure to all the Heirs of Promiſe, and how they are to be improved for the Saints Fort and Defence, Settlement and Incouragement in ſhaking and backſliding times. By <hi>O. Heywood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cloſet-prayer a Chriſtian Duty: Or, a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 6. By <hi>O. Heywood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Baptiſmal Bonds renewed. Being ſome Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 5. By <hi>O. H.</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Meetneſs for Heaven promoted in ſome brief Meditations upon <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. 12. Diſcovering the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and neceſſity of habitual and actual Meetneſs for Heaven here, in all that hope for Heaven hereafter. By <hi>O. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Epiſtolary Diſcourſe on the great aſſiſtances to a Chriſtians Faith, and for a more Intire Reſt and Aſſurance in the higheſt Trials and Adventures thereof. With a Second Part, upon the Preſent Times, and theſe rare Viciſſitudes of Providence in the Publick State of <hi>Britain</hi> in this Age. To which an Appendix is added in the Cloſe. By <hi>R. Fleming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Earthquakes; as they are Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural and Premonitory Signs to a Nation; with
<pb facs="tcp:43846:67"/> a reſpect to what hath occurred in this Year 1692. And ſome ſpecial Reflections thereon. As alſo on that Security and Aſſurance of Mind, which is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in the Light and Power of Religion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the greateſt Surprizals and Terrors of Senſe. With ſome Enquiry upon the Grounds, both of our Fears and Hopes, as to the publick State of the Church of Chriſt in this Day. By the Author of the Fulfilling of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The Confirming Work of Religion: Or its Great Things made plain, by their Primary Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and Demonſtrations. Whereby the meaneſt in the Church, may ſoon be made able to render a Rational account of their Faith. Written by <hi>R. Fleming,</hi> Author of the Fulfilling of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>A Defence of Mr. <hi>M. H</hi>'s. Brief Enquiry into the Nature of Schiſm, and the Vindication of it. With Reflections upon a Pamphlet called the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And a Brief Hiſtorical Account of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity, from the Reformation to this Preſent Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi>'s Alarm: Being an account of God's moſt Conſiderable Diſpenſations of Mercy and Judgment towards theſe Kingdoms for Fourteen Years laſt paſt. And alſo, of the ſeveral ſorts of Sins and Sinners therein; Eſpecially the Murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers againſt the Preſent Government. With an Earneſt Call to ſpeedy Humiliation, Supplication and Reformation, as the Chief Means of Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Majeſties Counſels and Preparations. Dedicated to the King and Queen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:68"/>
            <p> A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr. <hi>Thomas Shewell,</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Coventry.</hi> Who went up well into the Pulpit, <hi>Jan.</hi> 15. and having Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Named the Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12. was ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by an Apoplexy, and dyed within a few Hours. By <hi>William Tongue,</hi> Miniſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
            <p>The Good of Early Obedience. By <hi>M. Mead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Practical Expoſ. on the 130. <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Grace and Duty of being Spiritual Mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>The Declaration of the Glorious Miſtory of the Perſon of Chriſt. Theſe three by <hi>J. Owen,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Redemption of Time, the Duty and Wiſdom of Chriſtians in evil days. By <hi>S. Wade</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Hamerſmith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Vanity of Man, being a Diſcourſe, fitted for Funeral occaſions. By <hi>S. Shaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Several Diſcourſes concerning the actual Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God in three Parts.</p>
            <p>Above one hundred Sermons on the <hi>Canticles.</hi> Theſe two by the Reverend <hi>John Collings,</hi> D. D. of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43846:68"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
